<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lyon disturbed</title>
            <author>Grybius, Johannes.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2164B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223700</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833985</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833985</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38464</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42274)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38464)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1833:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lyon disturbed</title>
                  <author>Grybius, Johannes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>55, [1] p., [28] leaves of plates : ports., maps  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Steven Swart,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[A]t Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1672]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Johannes Grybius by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Title page fully engraved.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from title page; date of publication from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Colophon reads: Faithfully translated out of Dutch into English, according to the copy printed at Amsterdam by Steven Swart, bookseller. Novemb. 30. 1672.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 3: The lyon disturbed: containing an historicall relation of the most remarkable passages since the beginning of this war, betwixt the United Provinces, France, England, Colen, and the Bishop of Munster, unto this present.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; engraved title page damaged along inner margin; some plates backed; copy closely trimmed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dutch War, 1672-1678 --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  1648-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  1648-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:38464:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>THE LYON DISTURBED</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Amſterdam by Steven Swart</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38464:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38464:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:38464:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38464:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Gusman Fonseca</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>GUSMAN FONSECA DE HARO GRAEF van MONTERY Goevernuer Vande Spaenſche Nederlanden</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:38464:4"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:38464:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE LYON DISTURBED: <hi>Containing</hi> An Hiſtoricall Relation of the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Paſſages ſince the beginning of this War, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the United Provinces, France, England, Colen, and the Bishop of Munſter, unto this preſent.</head>
            <div type="year">
               <head>ANNO 1671.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N January a German Prince wrote unto one of the nobleſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of the Low Countries, admiring that people were ſo ſecure in Holland, and not more awakened, becauſe of the great preparations of War by the French and their Creatures, which he verily fore-ſaw to tend to nothing elſe, but the invaſion of the Netherlands. <hi>Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaniem maxime Mars odit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Febr. the Bishop of Munſter took on many Officers in ſervice, pretending his own ſecurity, which <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſed the States, as ſuſpecting him, to chooſe four Horſe and five Foot Regiments, appointing their ſeveral Places of muſtering of them.</p>
               <p>April 23. The King of France began his journey to the Spanish Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, which being in great Pomp and attendance, for to take a view of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, cauſed not a little fear to the Spaniard. But the Earl of Monterie held a vigilant Eye; yea, England it ſelf would ſeem to be awakened, ſecuring their Coaſts. This State alſo took care both for Ships at Sea, and ſtrengthening the Gariſons on the ſide of Flanders.</p>
               <p>In May, when the French Court was at Dunkirk, abundance of French and English Gentry came to and fro for to view the Courts, which by both the Kings were ſo highly entertained, that it was judged far to ſurpaſs common civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and ſomthing elſe to lurk under it, as afterward did plainly appear.</p>
               <p>In July, upon the tidings of the ſickneſs of the Duke d' Anjou, the King return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed home, and arrived at St. Germain the 17. dito, finding his Son but a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore departed.</p>
               <p>In Auguſt, beſide the continual taking on of Soldiers, and preparing Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins, an 187. Commiſſions were ſent forth from Paris, beſide Expreſſes to Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, Genua, Switſerland, Savoy, Venice, Luqua, Corſica and Scotland, with other places, for to leavy Regiments, and whole France through, Sea-Equipage was haſtened. At which time the States Fleet was before the Wielings, and the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38464:5"/>
Eſquadron of Admiral van Gent was met by the Merlin, commanded by Captain Crow, ſent over to fetch the Ambaſſadrix Temple from the Hague; who making a bravado, would have the whole Eſquadron to ſtrike, but as not having ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently inſiſted, he was at his return clapt up in the Tower, which buſineſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved afterwards the greateſt pretence of the English to their breach of the league between us.</p>
               <p>In September, Soldiers were preſſed both in England, Scotland and Yreland, for France, under pretext of recruting Douglas his Regiment, but Indeed of greater concern; it being afterward known that above 12000. were raiſed for the French ſervice.</p>
               <p>In Octob. this State perceiving the mighty warlike preparations on every ſide, and that vaſt ſums of money were ſent from France to England, and ma<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y English, Scotch and Irish Soldiers were shipt over from Dover to Calis; they reſolved alſo to increaſe their Militia, and to form a nearer inſtruction about a Captain General, which had ſomwhile been in deliberation.</p>
               <p>In Novemb. The French were yet buſie to form Magaſins in Luyk, Bon, Nuys, pretending it to be for the Bishop of Colen's ſervice againſt the City; but in the mean while, abundance of French entred upon divers pretences the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of Overmaſe &amp; along the Rhyne, which awakened Montrey, to viſite and provide the conſiderable Places of his Government as far as Navagnie: The States alſo by their Committees viſited their Frontiers, and reſolved againſt Spring to ſet forth a Fleet of 72. Ships, and by their Edicts forbad the bringing in, buying, ſelling or conſumption, of French Wine, Vineger, Paper, Canvas, and Cheſnuts.</p>
               <p>In Decemb. This State perceiving the mighty increaſe of the French Forces, and their great endeavours to gain England, Spain, Sweden and Germany, on their ſide; ſent a friendly Letter to be delivered by their Ambaſſador de Groot unto the King, who was kept from his audience the ſpace of a Moneth: but in the mean while, in the Hague on the 17. dito a defenſive League was (much againſt the will of France and England) concluded, betwixt this State and the Miniſters of Spain, and afterward was ratified and delivered over on both ſides.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A LETTER to the King of France.</head>
                     <p>MAy it pleaſe your Majeſty. After ſerious conſideration of that bounty, which the Kings your Progenitors, have alwayes shewed to this State, we could not without regret give credence unto the reports abroad, that thoſe mighty preparations for War in your Kingdome should be intended againſt us, which nevertheleſs by reaſon of advertiſements from all parts, and the management by your State Officers in the Courts of Kings and Princes round about, doth cauſe us to ſuspect. We therefore have ſtrictly ſearched, whither there might not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the management of our affairs be found an occaſion to move your Majeſty, tö decline that friendship, wherewith it hath pleaſed your Majeſty to honour us unto this preſent; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found nothing to accuſe our ſelves, nor for which we have been reproved by your Majeſty, we could not imagine, that the Juſtice which is exerciſed in your Kingdome, would permit your Majeſty to improve your Armes againſt your moſt faithfull and ancient Allies, without any
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38464:5"/>
foregoing manifeſtation of thoſe difficulties, of which you required reparation. And really, it is ſo far from us to give any juſt cauſe unto your Majeſty, or in any thing to come short of the agreement concluded in Paris Decemb. 1662. that we apprehend, that we have obſerved the ſame with all ſtrictneſs and care, and do offer without any delay, to make ſatisfaction, if through miſtake we have come short thereof. It is true, Great Sir, that for ſome time, there hath not been that Compliance as to Sea affairs and Merchandiſe; but this was very much to our griefe, neither have we omitted anything that might juſtly be required of us to prevent, and wholly to remove the troubles that have fallen out on either ſide, even as we are ready yee to do, and not onely as to that, but in whatſoever may fully teſtifie to your Majeſty our earneſt deſire, to render unto you the honour and high eſteem we are obliged unto as to your Perſon and Worth, and to give you all the contentment, which you could deſire from your beſt and moſt affectionate Allies, for the reſtoring of Trade at Sea, and Traffick in the ſame way, as it was at our laſt agreement; yea, in reſpect of our condeſcention to your intereſt, to go to the uttermoſt, we are able without prejudice to what we ſtand bound to other Confederates. To be short, Royal Sir, we do not believe to juſtifie thoſe martial prepares, which are both at Sea and Land, according to the intelligence we daily receive; but we would aſſure your Majeſty, that we do it not with purpoſe to wrong any, but through extream neceſſity, and moſt ſtrong obligations to defend our State and Subjects: and that it shall be our joy to lay down our Armes, when it shall pleaſe your Majeſty to free us from thoſe troubles, which that War doth bring upon us, that ſeemeth near approaching on all ſides, aſſuring our ſelves, we ought not to ſtand in fear of yours. We have given Commiſſion unto our Ambaſſador D' Groot, to deſire a particular audience as to theſe things by your Majeſty, and to propound them more at large, with addition of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may ſerve to aſſure your Majeſty of the uprightneſs of our intents. Here we will break off and not further enlarge; but onely to beg of God to preſerve your Majeſty.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Written in the Hague <date>Decemb. 10. 1671.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="year">
               <head>ANNO 1672.</head>
               <p>Januar. 2. The Interim agreement between the Bishop and City, was ſigned at Colen, by which alſo the City was neceſſitated to cauſe Bamphields Regiment being in ſervice of the States, to quit the City, which by reaſon of many obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, the French urging to muſter them, and to take out all of their Nation among them, was retarded untill the 4 of February, but without moleſtation then departed to Rijnberck, and other Places on the Rhijn, when it manifeſtly appeared, that the French, Munſters, and Colens deſignes, were nothing elſe, but to fall upon us, to which end the Bishop of Colen claimed the delivery of Rijnberck, and the Bishop of Munſter the Children of the Earle of Benthem: In the mean while, nothing more noyſed than raiſing of Soldiers, and shipping over of numbers of English to France; and then becauſe of the low waters, many flat boats were made ready here to lay upon the Rivers.</p>
               <p>Febr. 4. The Ambaſſador d'Groot firſt obtained an hearing, to deliver the States Letter to the King: receiving for anſwer that this Letter was already communicated to him from other Princes, and that about the Spring it would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear whereto this arming tended, to which end alſo the 6. dito a Letter was ſent to the States in anſwer as followeth:</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:38464:6"/>
                     <p>MUch endeared Great Friends and Allies: By the Lord d'Groot, your Ambaſſador Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary to us, we have underſtood what was on your behalf to be declared to us, and have received out of his hand of Decemb. <hi>10.</hi> the Letter ordered by you to be given unto us. We were well pleaſed in it to find the acknowledgement you make to have received at divers occaſions the tokens of the goodneſs of the Kings our Progenitors: but we could have wished you had not forgotten what hath fallen out ſince we came to the Crown, the remembrance whereof would have prevented you of judging ſo ſincerely of your tranſactions to us ward as you doe, in the managing of your affairs ſince that time, you might have called to mind, that you have not alwayes obſerved that fidelity, which our ancient confederacy did oblige unto, and that we have not failed in your urgent neceſſities to afford you requiſite aſſiſtance, for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your State: If ſo, it may be, the innovation you made in trading ſince <hi>1662.</hi> would not have ſeemed ſo excuſable unto you as you make it, and which we are willing to referre to the judgment of them that have leſſe intereſt in it than we. If what you acknowledge, be true, that Juſtice be the rule of our actings, and that you are ſatisfied in the conſidering of our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, then ought you not to be troubled at our taking up of Armes; We grant that ſince our laſt journey to Flanders, we have increaſed our Bands, to improve our foot in the works of our Forts, and to difend our Subjects from danger, threatned by the more than ordinary number of Foot and Horſe by you raiſed, and the Fleet you kept before our Coaſts: as alſo becauſe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune Addreſſes of your State Miniſters at the Court of moſt Princes, for to combine with you againſt our Crown: Wherein we followed the Law of ſage providence, and what the defence of our people obliged us to. We would therefore let you know, that we will go forward with our arming, both at Sea and Land, and when it shall be brought to that height, we have propoſed to do, we shall ſo improve, as we shall think becoming our Honour, of which we are bound to give no account to any, aſſuring our ſelves, that God will bleſſe our righteous undertakings, and that shall be owned of all Potentates, who have not ſuffered themſelves to be prejudiced by thoſe evill impreſſions, which now for a long time hath been endeavoured to be done. This was our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to give in anſwer to you Letter, although it was written not ſo much for us, as to ſtirre up the Princes againſt us, in whoſe Courts it was common, before we had received the ſame. We pray God, very dear great Friends and Allies, to keep you in his holy protection. Written at <hi>St. Germein de Laye. 6. Januar. 1672.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your good Friend and Ally, LOUIS. LE TELLIER.</signed>
                        <hi>Was ſubſcribed Under it,</hi>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>8. Dito, The Ambaſſador Downing, who ſome dayes had been in the Hague, made his publick Entrance, but little ſatisfaction was taken as to himſelf, and not much exſpected from his negotiation. About this time, the Lords, of Ameron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen went to the Elector of Brandenburg, and of Braſſer to the Princes of Lunen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, for to treat with them about ſupplies of Auxiliary Troups.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Willem Hendrick de III</figDesc>
                  <head>WILLEM HENDRICK DE III by de gratie Godts. PRINCE van ORANIE erf Stadthonder Cap: Gen: van Holl: Zeel: etc:</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Febr. 4. The Ambaſſador Downing had his farewell audience, declaring that foraſmuch as he could not obtain an anſwer to his memorial &amp; iterated inſtances about ſtriking the Flag, he was ordered to return home. Although the State had divers times proffered to give due ſatisfaction, in caſe all pretences were brought in to be together treated on: which alſo the ſaid States by their Letter had ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the King: but Downing proteſted to have expreſſe order to treat of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, before ſatisfaction was made about the Flag, which the States declining he returned home, and ſoon after his return was put into the Tower, and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of ſome of his Places of honour, the cauſe not being diſcovered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> onely it was given out that he came back before he had order: although afterward it appeared that the agreement betwixt France and England was fully concluded, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the 12. dito, ſo that it ſeemeth this was onely done to abuſe us.</p>
               <p>9. Dito, The States of Holland took on Officers for 8. Regiments of Horſe, and 5. on Foot, and the 12. dito by proviſion for two more: which choice of Officers was pro rato alſo made in the other Provinces. In France, Patents were given out for 20000. Foot, and 6000. Horſe more: The Bishops of Colen and Munſter alſo gathered Forces amain. England haſtened their Fleet under the Duke of York Admiral: Here alſo they neglected nothing which might haſten their Fleet.</p>
               <p>25. Dito, After infinite conſultations and diſputes, at length his Highneſs was appointed Captain General over the Forces of the State, but with all poſſible reſtrictions, an Oath being taken of him, that he might never ſeek to be Stat-holder of any of the Provinces, nor accept of it, if he should be deſired to it. Hereupon his Highneſs treated the Deputies of Knighthood and Cities of Holland with a Royal Feaſt, March 1.</p>
               <p>March 4. The froſt, which this Winter was very long, now ceaſing, here hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily arrived a great and exceeding rich Fleet of Merchandiſe, with their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyes, having laid long at the Iſle of Wight, fearing they might have been there arreſted.</p>
               <p>14. Dito, The Ambaſſador Meerman was ſent to England, for to prevent, if poſſible, the breach feared, of which there was ſome hopes, becauſe the Ships were ſuffered without any moleſtation to depart from the Iſle of Wight, and the Embargo of their Ships in England was made nul; and eſpecially becauſe many English and Scotch Ships obtained Pas for Holland: On the other hand the mighty preparations made both in England and France, promiſed but little good to come from theſe overtures for peace; the rather becauſe our Ambaſſador be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come thither, was certified, there was little appearance thereof, it now being too late, which perhaps if had come ſooner might have been attained.</p>
               <p>20. Dito, Digby declared in France, that by reaſon of Downings miſtake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his Maſter the King of England, would be forced to begin the work two moneths before it was intended, and it eaſily deſerveth credit, that it was not their deſign to declare themſelves ſo ſoon, ſo many Ships having ſo lately obtained Paſport<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for Holland, and the ſeaſon of the year not yet fit for a Field expedition.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:38464:8"/>22. Dito, the Smirna's Meſſina's, and Mallaga's Convoy, returning with 50. Ships richly laden, among which alſo were five Convoyers from Gales, to whom the Convoy from Lisbon adjo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned, being 20. in number, by a Catch from Zealand in the Chanel were warned, not to ſail into any of the English Havens, or to truſt their Ships, whereupon they alſo made all things ready for defence: &amp; the very ſame night 4. English Ships appeared, shooting but without Bullet, but ſoon after, 12. more, who fired with shot luſtily on ours, continuing all the next day, and the day after, being reinforced with other Ships, they fell upon the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Men; but were ſo ſaluted, that with their battered Ships and many ſlain, they were conſtrained to return home, paying dearly for their prey taken, viz. one Smirna's, one Meſſina's, with two other Ships of ſmall value, all the reſt getting ſafe into our Harbors, being a wonderfull providence of God, thus gently to awaken us, ſeeing the whole Fleet was in danger to have fallen into their hands, or we might have been warned with a greater diſaſter. And though the King by this unexpected and unjuſt attacque, did manifeſt what his purpoſe was, yet would they ſeem to colour it upon pretence of unwillingneſſe to ſtrike, and to have ſatisfaction by conſtraint; But they were Enemies in heart, as our foregoing obſervations do ſufficiently declare, eſpecially the Kings Declaration of War, following hereupon the 29. dito.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="declaration">
                           <head>His Majeſties Declaration againſt the States General of the United Provinces of the Low-Countreys.</head>
                           <opener>
                              <signed>Charles R.</signed>
                           </opener>
                           <p>WE have been alwayes ſo zealous for the Quiet of Chriſtendom, and ſo carefull not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade any other Kingdome or State, that We hope the World will do Us the Juſtice to believe, that it is nothing but inevitable neceſſity forceth Us to the reſolution of taking up Armes.</p>
                           <p>Immediately upon Our Reſtauration to Our Crowns, the firſt work We undertook, was the eſtablishing of Peace, and the ſetling a good Correſpondence between Us and Our Neighbours; and in particular, Our care was, to conclude a ſtrict League with the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> upon ſuch equal Terms, as would certainly not have been broken, if any obligations could have kept them within the bounds of Friendship or Juſtice.</p>
                           <p>This League was maintained inviolable on Our part. But in the year <hi>1664.</hi> we were ſtirred up by the Complaints of Our People, and the unanimous Vote of Both Our Houſes of Parliament, finding it a vain attempt to endeavour the proſperity of Our Kingdoms by peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wayes at home, whilſt Our Subjects were ſtill expoſed to the Injuries and Oppreſſions of thoſe States abroad.</p>
                           <p>That whole Summer was ſpent in Negotiations and endeavours on Our ſide, to bring them to reaſonable Terms, which notwithſtanding all We could do, proved at length ineffectual: for the more we purſued them with friendly Propoſitions, the more obſtinately they kept off from agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with us.</p>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                              <p>BON</p>
                           </figure>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                              <p>LEGNIGH</p>
                           </figure>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                              <p>KERPEN</p>
                           </figure>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>portrait of Karel de II</figDesc>
                              <head>KAREL DE II by de Gratie Godts KONINCK van GROOT BRITTANIE</head>
                           </figure>
                           <p>In the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> 
                              <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>hey went a little further; For by an Article in the ſame Treaty, we were to reſtore <hi>Surinam</hi> into their hands, and by Articles upon the place confirmed by that Treaty, that they were to give Liberty to all Our Subjects in that Colony, to Tranſport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Eſtates into any other of Our Plantations. In purſuance of this Agreement, We delivered up the Place, and yet they detained all Our men in it; onely Major <hi>Baniſter</hi> they ſent away priſoner, for but deſiring to remove according to the Articles. Our Ambaſſadour complaining of this behaviour, after two years ſollicitation, obtained an Order for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of thoſe Articles: But when We ſent Commiſſioner<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, and two Shipt to bring Our Men away, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> (according to their former practice in the buſineſs of <hi>Poleroon</hi> for above fourty years together) ſent private Orders contradictory to thoſe they had owned to Us in Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick; and ſo the onely effect of Our Commiſſioners journey thither, was to bring away ſome few of the pooreſt of our Subjects, and the Prayers and Cryes of the Moſt conſiderable and weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt of them, for relief out of that Captivity. After this, We made Our Complaints by Our Letter in Auguſt laſt to the <hi>States General,</hi> wherein We deſired an Order to their Governours there, for the full obſervance of thoſe Articles; yet to this time We could never receive one word of anſwer or ſatisfaction.</p>
                           <p>But it is no wonder that they venture at theſe Outrages upon Our Subjects in remote parts, when they dare be ſo bold with Our Royal Perſon, and the Honour of this Nation ſo near Us, as in their own Countrey, there being ſcarce a Town within their Territories that is not filled with abuſive Pictures, and falſe Hiſtorical Medals and Pillars; ſome of which have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the publick view by command of the <hi>States</hi> themſelves, and in the very time when we were joyned with them in united Councels for the ſupport of the Triple League; and the Peace of Chriſtendom. This alone were cauſe ſufficient for Our diſpleaſure, and the reſentment of all Our Subjects. But We are urged to it by conſiderations yet nearer to Us, then what onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to our Self; the Safety of Our Trade, upon which the wealth and proſperity of our People depends, the preſervation of them abroad from violence and oppreſsion, and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to affront us almoſt within Our very Ports, are the things which move Our juſt Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt them.</p>
                           <p>The Right of the <hi>Flagg</hi> is ſo ancient, that it was one of the firſt Prerogatives of Our Royal Predeceſſors, and ought to be the laſt from which this Kingdom should ever depart. It was never queſtioned, and it was expreſly acknowledged in the Treaty at <hi>Breda;</hi> and yet this laſt Summer it was not onely violated by their Commanders at Sea, and that violation afterwards juſtified at the <hi>Hague,</hi> but it was alſo repreſented by them in moſt Courts of Chriſtendom as ridiculous for Us to demand. An ungratefull Inſolence! That they should contend with Us about the Dominion of theſe Seas, who even in the Reign of Our Royal Father, thought it an Obligation to be permitted to Fish in them, by taking of Licenſes, and for a Tribute; and who owe their being now in a condition of making this Diſpute, to the Protection of Our Anceſtors, and the Valour and Bloud of their Subjects.</p>
                           <p>Notwithſtanding all theſe provocations, We patiently exſpected Satisfaction, not being wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to expoſe the Peace of Chriſtendom for Our particular reſentments, whileſt they ceaſed not on their parts to endeavour to provoke the moſt Chriſtian King againſt Us; of which they thought themſelves ſo ſecure, that for above theſe Twelve months their Miniſters here have threatned Us with it.</p>
                           <p>At length, hearing nothing from them, We ſent another Ambaſſador to them, who after ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38464:11"/>
preſsing Memorials in Our Name, could receive no Anſwer, till after he had declared his Revocation. Then they offered a Paper to this effect, That in this Conjuncture they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to Strike to Us, if We would aſsiſt them againſt the French; but upon conditiön, that it should never be taken for a Preſident hereafter to their prejudice.</p>
                           <p>Since the return of Our ſaid Ambaſſador, They have ſent an Extraordinary One to Us, who in a moſt extraordinary manner has given Us to underſtand, That he can offer us no Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction till he hath ſent back to his Maſters.</p>
                           <p>Wherefore, deſpairing now of any good effect of a further Treaty, We are compelled to take up Arms in Defence of the Ancient Prerogative of Our Crowns, and the Glory, and Safety of Our Kingdoms; And We put Our Truſt in God, that He will give us His Aſſiſtance in this Our juſt Undertaking, ſince We had no way left to defend Our People from the Artifice of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Peace, but by the Valour of Our Subjects in War.</p>
                           <p>We have therefore thought fit to Declare, and do hereby Declare, That We will proſecute War both by Sea and Land againſt the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> and all their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and Inhabitants. Hereby enjoyning Our moſt dear and entirely beloved Brother the <hi>Duke of York</hi> Our High Admiral, Our Lieutenants of Our ſeveral Counties, Governors of Our Forts and Garriſons, and all other Officers and Soldiers under them by Sea and Land, to oppoſe all the attempts of the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> or their Subjects, and to do, and execute all Acts of hoſtility in the proſecution of this War againſt the ſaid <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> their Vaſſals, Subjects, and Inhabitants; Willing and Requiring all Our Subjects to take notice of the ſame, Whom We henceforth ſtraightly forbid, on pain of Death, to hold any Correſpondence or Communication with the ſaid <hi>States General,</hi> or their Subjects, (thoſe only excepted who are neceſsitated thereunto for the withdrawing their Perſons and Eſtates out of the <hi>United Provinces</hi>) And becauſe there are remaining in our Kingdoms many Subjects of the <hi>States General of the United Provinces,</hi> We do Declare, and give Our Royal Word, that all ſuch of the Dutch Nation, as shall demean themſelves dutifully towards Us, and not correſpond with Our Enemies shall be ſafe in their Perſons and Eſtates, and free from all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation and trouble of any kind.</p>
                           <p>And further We do Declare, That if any of the Low-Countrey Subjects, either out of Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Us, or Our Government, or becauſe of the Oppreſſion they meet with at home, shall come into Our Kingdoms, they shall be by Us protected in their Perſons and Eſtates.</p>
                           <p>And whereas We are engaged by a Treaty to ſupport the Peace made at <hi>Aix la Chappelle,</hi> We do finally Declare, That notwithſtanding the proſecution of this War; We will maintain the true Intent and Scope of the ſaid Treaty, and that in all the Alliances, which We have or shall make in the progreſs of this War, We have and will take care, to preſerve the Ends thereof in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable, unleſs provoked to the contrary.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>
                                 <hi>Given at Our Court at</hi> Whitehall <date>
                                    <hi>the 17. day of March, in the 24. year of Our Reign, 1672.</hi>
                                 </date>
                              </dateline>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>This was published in London the 7. April, and the very ſame day the French King Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed War againſt this State; which afterward was alſo done by the Bishop of Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. The frivolous reaſons and idle pretences, I referre to the judgement of the Reader, it being ſufficient barely to mention them.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Louis de Bourbon de XIIII</figDesc>
                  <head>LOUIS DE BOURBON DE XIIII by de gratie Godts. KONINCK van VRANCKRYCK. en Navarre etc:</head>
               </figure>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38464:12"/>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:38464:12"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="declaration">
                           <head>The Declaration of the King of France, by which his Majeſty after reſolution to make War upon the States of Holland, forbiddeth all Correſpondence or Trading with them. 6. April 1672. By the King.</head>
                           <p>The disſatisfaction his Majeſty hath had in the management of the States General of the United Provinces ſome years ſince, in their actings toward him; and it being come to that paſſe, that his Majeſty can no longer but with ſtain to his honour connive at the unworthineſſe acted againſt him by ſuch manner of doing, which ſo little agreeth with the great obligations, wherewith his Majeſty and the Kings his Predeceſſors, have ſo liberaly filled up the meaſure unto them: ſo that his Majeſty hath declared, and doth declare by theſe preſents ſigned by his own hand, that he hath arreſted and fully reſolved to make war with the ſaid States General of the United Provinces, both by Sea and Land.</p>
                           <p>To this end, his Majeſty commandeth all his Subjects, Vaſſals, and Servants to fall upon the Hollanders; and hath, &amp; doth forbid them from hence forward to hold any Correſpondence, Trade or Intelligence with them upon pain of Death. And his Majeſty to this end hath henceforward revoked, and doth revoke, all Permiſſion, Paſports, Safegards or Free-paſſes, which either by himſelf or his Deputies, or other his Officers, may have been granted contrary to theſe, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts the ſame as null and of no worth, forbidding all and everyone, who ever they be, to have any regard unto them.</p>
                           <p>And his Majeſty commandeth and appointeth the Lord Earl of Vermandois, Great-Maſter, Head and Superintendent General of the Navigation and Commerce of this Kingdom; The Marshàls of France; the Governors and Lieutenants General for his Majeſty in his Provinces and Armies, The Field-Marshàls, Colonels, chief Officers, Captains, Heads and Leaders of his Soldiers whither Horſe or Foot, French or Strangers, and all other Officers whom it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, that they cauſe the Contents hereof to be executed every one in his Place throughout their command and Juriſdiction, for ſuch is his Majeſties pleaſure, who willeth that theſe shall be published and affixed in all his Cities, and Sea-Coaſt Towns, and in all Havens and other Places of his Kingdom, where it shall be requiſite, that none may pretend ignorance hereof. Acted in the Caſtle of Verſailles the <hi>6.</hi> April <hi>1672.</hi> Signed <hi>Louis,</hi> and yet lower <hi>Le Tellier.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>It is ordered, that <hi>Charles Canto,</hi> ſworn Herald of the King, shall Proclaim and cauſe to be affixed in all places of this City, Suburbs, Provoſtships and Markgraefships of Paris, where need shall require this Ordinance of the King of the <hi>6.</hi> of this preſent moneth and year, that no ignorance be pretended. Signed <hi>De la Reinie.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Read and proclaimed at the ſound of Trumpet, together by affixion in all the common and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Croſs-ſtreets and Suburbs of Paris, by me <hi>Charles Canto,</hi> Ordinary ſworn Herald of the King in the ſaid City, Provoſtships and Markgraefships of Paris, in proclaiming where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I was accompanied with five Trumpetters, viz. <hi>Proſme Trouſſon, Endime du Bos,</hi> ſworn Trumpetters of this King, and three more, on Thurſday the <hi>7.</hi> April <hi>1672.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Subſcribed <hi>CANTO.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Now it was high time to haſten all warlike preparations, the Ambaſſadors of the States the Lord Meerman, and D'Groot, returning from England and France, re infecta; and the Generals being choſen both of the French and our Armies.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="list_of_generals">
                           <pb n="12" facs="tcp:38464:13"/>
                           <head>The Generals of the French Army.</head>
                           <list>
                              <head>The Army of the King.</head>
                              <item>
                                 <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                                    <desc>•…</desc>
                                 </gap>nſieur the Duke of Orleans, Gene-Mraliſſimo.</item>
                              <item>
                                 <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                                    <desc>•…</desc>
                                 </gap>arshal de Turenne, Captain Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</item>
                              <item>Earl of Soiſons, Marquis de Rochefort.</item>
                              <item>Earl of Lude, Earl or Gadaigne, Duke de la Favillades</item>
                              <item>Earl de Lorge; Lieutenants General.</item>
                              <item>Chevalier de Loraine, Marquis de Genlis, Martinet, de Montal, Field-marshals.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>The Army of the Peince of Conde.</head>
                              <item>Marshal d'Humieres, de Bellefonds, Captains General.</item>
                              <item>Foucault, de St. Arbre, Earl de Guiche, Lieutenants General.</item>
                              <item>Earl du Pleſſis, du Nogent, Magalotti, Field-marshals.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>The Army of the Marshal de Crequi.</head>
                              <item>Monſ. de Nancre, Lieutenant General.</item>
                              <item>Earl de Vaubrun, Monſieur du Pleſſis, Field-marshals.</item>
                              <item>Duke of Luxenburgh, General of the Army of the Confederates.</item>
                              <item>Monſ. de la Valiere, Field-marshal.</item>
                              <item>Monſ. le Breſt, Field-marshal towards Catalonia.</item>
                              <item>Monſ. d'Elbeuf, General of a Body at the Sea-ſide.</item>
                           </list>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>The King before the ſetting forth of the Army, having commanded the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shals d'Humieres, Bellefonds and Crequi, that if the Armies come to be conjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or in abſence of the Princes of the Bloud, they should for the time of this expedition ſubmit to the orders of Turenne, which they excuſing were put by in diſgrace, and Chamely, Gadaigne and Navaile, put in their room, but after ſome time the former were replaced, yet with promiſe of ſubmiſſion to Turenne.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="list_of_generals">
                           <head>Generals of the Army of the States of the United Provinces.</head>
                           <list>
                              <item>The Prince of Orange, Captain Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</item>
                              <item>Prince Maurits, and the Lord Wirts, Field-marshals.</item>
                              <item>The Rijngrave Senior, General of the Horſe.</item>
                              <item>The Lord of Zuileſtein, General of the Foot.</item>
                              <item>The Earl of Hornes, General of the Artillery.</item>
                              <item>John van Welderen, Earl of Naſſau, Lieutenant Generals of the Horſe.</item>
                              <item>Alua, The Earl Koningſmarck, Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants Generals of the Foot.</item>
                              <item>Mombas, Steenhuyſe, Commiſſary Generals of the Horſe.</item>
                              <item>Kirpatrick, the Earl of Stirum, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant Majors.</item>
                           </list>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Afterward was choſen for the third Field-marshal, the Earl of Waldeck and Kuylenburg.</p>
               <p>The 13. dito, The State proclaimed a general faſt againſt the 4. of May; and ſo forwards to be kept upon every firſt Wedneſday of the Month; and it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to encreaſe the Militia, both for the State in general, as alſo for Holland in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38464:13"/>
particular, of which capitulations were formed to raiſe them of outlandish Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: Alſo ſome of our Foot Regiments were ſent over to the Spaniards, to be in Garriſon, in Namen, Valencijn, and other places, and on the other hand to us came ſome Regiments of Spanish Horſe, of which ſome Companies were ſent to Maſtricht.</p>
               <p>16. dito, The Elector of Colen published a Manifeſt (though his whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of Colen and Luyck was already a Magaſin for France,) that he would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain neutrality, forbidding the acting of any hoſtility againſt the Subject of this State, unto all in his Dominion; but in truth, this was onely done for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us.</p>
               <p>26. dito, Was the time appointed for the ſitting of the Parliament at London, which inſtantly was prorogued without doing of any thing, to the 30. of Octob. and in place of Ayſcue deceaſed, Sr. Joſeph Jordan was placed jin the Fleet, to which the Duke of York went the 29. dito, to ſet to Sea: and the Duke of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth prepared himſelf for France, there to command thoſe of the English Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and in ſpecial his own Regiment in the Kings Army, and ſoon after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted with many of the Gentry.</p>
               <p>27. dito, After that the French King had for a long time been raiſing an huge Hoſt, which was eſteemed to amount to above 300000. men, which reckoning all the Pages, Lacquyes, Coachmen, Carriers, Boyes, Krauwels, Pioniers, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Troſſes and Whores, might well be, for the Muſter-rowles amounted to 146270. Soldiers at leaſt, with Mortepaiſe, huge Artillery with an incredible quantity of Proviſion and Ammonition, both at home and in diverſe Magaſins abroad. Thus his Majeſty, having committed the management of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to the Queen and her Council, departed from Paris the 27. of April with the Marshal Turenne; three dayes together being ſpent in tranſporting of the Treine and Bagage, for which were imployed 40000. Horſes, with a ſufficient number of Carts and waggons. The 28. dito, the Duke Orleans with many Grandees followed, who took their march with his Majeſty by Nantevil, Soi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Lion, Rocroy, and the 5. of May arrived at Charleroy. The ſame day the Prince of Conde paſſed by la Ferte and Reims, and arrived the 30. at Sedan, for to come down with an Army apart: In the mean while, much shipping came down the Moeſel and Rijne, for to bring all manner of neceſſaries paſt Colen unto their Magaſin at Nuys, great numbers alſo longſt the Maſe to Luyck, and the Troups which lay ſpread abroad thoughout the Country of Colen, were now called together to Nuys, and the Bishop of Munſter alſo gathered his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery together, preparing for the Field.</p>
               <p>May the 6. at Colen on the Spree a treaty of mutual aſſiſtance and defence was concluded between Brandenburg and the Lord of Amerongen, in which Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg engaged to raiſe for the defence of this State 20000. men, to wit, 12000. Foot, and eight thouſand Horſe, to which Holland was to furniſh the half of the levie mony, viz. 120000. Rijcksdollers, and for the pay of every Regiment conſiſting of 500. Horſe, 4977. Rijcksdollers to ſtulvers, and every Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Foot, conſiſting of a 1000. 4214. Rijcksdollers 4. ſtuivers per Month, beſides for the Artillery and other inevitable expences 14841. Rijcks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dollers per Month, being together 79543. Rijcksdollers per Month, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38464:14"/>
that Brandenburg at his charges should provide 50. pieces, with all the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition and Artillery thereto belonging, obliging himſelf 2 months after the receipt of the firſt payment, to have his Army in readineſs; There was a Treaty alſo with the Princes of Lunenburg, but without effect: in the mean while our Army gathered near the Yſſel about Doesburg, and the retrenchment alongſt the Yſſel was compleated, whither the Prince with moſt of the chief Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders came, and the Forts at Staphorſt and Rouveen were with all diligence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, and the Army muſtered.</p>
               <p>9. dito, The French King having made a review of his Army near Charleroy, ſent the Marshal Turenne with 15000. men, 4000. Wagons, and 27. Canons, to march to the great Caſſey by Luyck, and Maſtricht, and himſelf followed with the gros of the Army, and on the 11, 12. and 13. dito, having lodged in three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places of the Spanish bounds, came the 14. dito into the countrey of Luyk, paſſing near by Navagne, and arrived the 18. dito at Viſé, where he ſtayed, and beſet Tongeren with French Soldiers: In the interim, dito 16 the Avantguard under Marshal Turrenne had ſurrounded, and shot upon Maſeyck, requiring them to deliver it up, and nothing, regarding the Luyckish neutrality poſſeſſed himſelf thereof, and Turenne entring it, ſaid that there a Magaſin for the King muſt be erected, and ſerve for a pas to the Armies, ſo departing, preſently the French fell at work to fortify the Town, demolishing whatever ſtood in their way. Hereby Maſtricht was as good as blockt up, and the rather becauſe Condé came on the other ſide of Maſtricht, with an Army of 35000. men, which was come marching from Sedan through Ardennes, longſt the overſide of the Maſe, ſo that it ſeemed, they intended to aſſault Maſtricht; of which there was no great fear, ſeeing it was well provided with all things neceſſary, and had a Garriſon of 12000. Soldiers, beſides the Citizens.</p>
               <p>14. dito, Upon the advice that our Fleet was at Sea, which at Schoonevelt yet waited for ſome of our ships, and that the French Vice Admiral the Earl d'Eſtré was come to Wight, The English Fleet under the Duke of York made out to Sea, to joyn with them: which had not our Fleet come a little too late might have been prevented, one of them that followed falling in our hands, was ſent up to Rotterdam: Our Fleet croſſing there about ſome time, and ſeeing the Enemies Fleet came not out, returned back to our coaſts.</p>
               <p>18. dito, The Bishop of Munſter deſirous to share in the enſuing war, published upon frivolous pretences a Weſtphalian Declaration of War againſt this State.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="declaration">
                           <head>Declaration of his Grace the Bishop of Munſter againſt the States of the United Provinces.</head>
                           <p>BE it known, that foraſmuch as by intercepted Letters and Perſons detained in Priſon, and by many other wayes, it is confeſſed and made evident, that in the United Provinces; many have been induced and miſted through mony and great promiſes of reward to labour by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their adherents to corrupt, and by great ſoms of mony to entice the Servants and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of our Gracious Lord of Munſter and Convey, to fire the Forts, Cities, and eſpecially the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſins of his Highneſs, and through ſuch horrid crimes to make the Senses poſſeſſors of his Grades Forts and Cities, and to debauch his Soldiers from their oath &amp; duty, having ſtirred up <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>ellion,
<pb facs="tcp:38464:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                              <figure>
                                 <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                                 <p>CHARLEROY</p>
                              </figure>
                              <figure>
                                 <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                                 <p>MAESTRIGHT</p>
                              </figure>
                              <pb facs="tcp:38464:15"/>
                              <pb n="15" facs="tcp:38464:15"/>
and revolts by ſuch damnable wayes: yea, have alſo not feared to conſpire againſt the very life it ſelf of his Grace, committing Crimen Aſſaſinatus againſt his Graces Perſon: Which thing alſo, horrible to relate, hath in his Country, Cities, Forts, Lordships, Towns and Villages been practiſed, many places ſet on fire, as verily ſuſpected to have been atchieved by theſe evill Doers; as hath been confeſſed and ocularly appeared: So as ſuch horrid actions have ſcarce ever been perpetrated by Barbarians and Turks. Wherefore his Grace, both in care to his own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as alſo to preſerve, aſmuch as poſſible may be his Graces Cities, Forts, Lordships, Towns and Subjects, in the Country from further dammage, doth command moſt graciouſly and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, all his High and Low Officers, whiter Civil or Military, all his common Soldiers and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects moſt ſtrictly to take care that none of theſe incendiaries and traytors be ſuffered to enter his Grates Dominions, which if any shall preſume, to ſeize upon them, and deliver them to the neareſt Garriſons, and whoever shall bring in any one of theſe, shall have a recompence of <hi>100.</hi> Rijcksdollers. But to the end, that hereby other honeſt and well-meaning people be not hindred to come into his Highneſſe Dominions, for to Trade in his Graces Cities and Country; they are required to ſignifie unto the Commanders and Officers where they firſt arrive, the cauſe of their coming, that ſo they may drive their trade and buſineſſe in his Graces Dominions, having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obtained a Pas from them. His often before mentioned Grace, doth alſo command the more carefully and with aſſurance, to prevent all treachery upon the higheſt arbitrary, and after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction upon pain of corporal punishment, as alſo confiſcation of Goods, that no man of what ſtate or quality ſoever within his Juriſdiction, thither Eccleſiaſtical or Laick, Civil or Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſon, do without conſent granted correſpond, with any of the ſaid Netherlands, by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of Letters or Commerce, ſo as all trading with them is, from hence forward unlawfull: and that no man may pretend ignorance thereby to excuſe himſelf, theſe preſents, shall in all our Cities, Towns, Lordships and Villages, as alſo in all Garriſons and elſewhere be publickly from the Pulpit proclaimed, and afterward in uſual Places affixed, that every one may have know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge hereof, witneſſe our own hand and printed ſecret Seal. Subſcribed at his reſidence in Ludgersburg the <hi>18.</hi> May <hi>1672.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Chriſtoff. Bernhardt. Locus Sigilli.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>18. dito, Here happily arrived the Fleet from St. Ubal about 80. ſail, of which ſome that went towards the Eaſt Sea were taken by Scotch Capers. The ſame dito, the States did of their meer bounty ſet at liberty all the detained English and Scotch ships, which about the time of the breach and ſome while after were with pas from the Duke of York come hither, to the number of 70. Merchant men and more, allowing them freely to depart with ships and lading, which the States by their laſt agreement were not bound to do, but might according to the Law of Arms have made them prize. The day following the States choſe Officers for the raiſing of four Regiments, and gave the Commander Stockheim an order to raiſe one Regiment more; alſo a part of our Foot, that had been quartered in the Spanish Netherland returned home, and the reſt followed ſoon after. All Holland through the Peſants were armed and muſtered, and 1375. of them were ſent from North-Holland to the Yſſel.</p>
               <p>18. dito, in open field the King of France held a great Councel of War with all his High Officers, and concluded to keep Maſtricht blockt up with 20000. men, and to march with the gros of the Army to the Rijn; Whereupon Condé the 21. dito brake up with his Army, paſſing through Gulicker-land, directly to Keyſers-Weert, where the 27. and 28. dito he paſſed the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38464:16"/>
Rijn over a Bridge of ships, and came the 1. of June before Weſel. Turenne with his Army followed him, and paſſing the Maes, marched directly to Nuys, and from thence by the weſt-ſide of the Rijn, Orſoy and Rijnberg, to Burick, where he arrived the 1. June. The King with his Army followed the 27. May, and 31. dito arrived near Nuys, where the Elector of Colen had made great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to entertain his Majeſty, but the King excuſing it, haſtened his march directly to Orſoy and Rijnberg, where he came 1. June.</p>
               <p>1. June, with break of day Orſoy and Rijnberg were ſurrounded by the King himſelf, Weſel by the Prince of Condé, and Burick which lay over againſt it, by Turenne: At the ſame time the Bishop of Munſter with his Troups, and ſome of Colens brake up from Benthem, and falling into Twente, ſurrounded the City Grol. But of theſe more in particular.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Orſoy,</hi> though a little, yet a ſtrong City, having 700. Soldiers in it, for defence whereof more then 2000. had been needfull, was by the King ſummoned June 1. but the Councel of War, conſiſting of the Colonel Moulet Commander, Major Koerbeeck, and 7. Captains with their under Officers, would not liſten, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to defend the City, wherefore the King was neceſſitated to plant his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, which the beſieged ſeeing and fearing the great power of the Enemy, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no hope of ſuccour, they began to deſpair, and to think upon good condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of agreement, and were conſtrained to deliver up themſelves the 3. dito, to the diſcretion of the King, onely reſerving Life and Goods, which accord the French not regarding, miſerably abuſed the Garriſon high and low, keeping them as priſoners of war.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>WEESEL</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>BURICK</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>RYNBERCK</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>ORSOY</p>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>Burick,</hi> right over againſt Weſel, being a ſmall Fortreſſe with 5. bulwarks, and ruined fortification, no reparation a long time having been done to it, three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſoldiers onely in it, alſo unprovided of Canons and Ammunition, having for their Governour Peckendam, with 3. Captains, was alſo beſieged the 1. of June by Turenne who (notwithſtanding the beſieged, conſidering their bad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, defended themſelves couragiouſly) advanced ſo ſtrongly, that on June 3. early in the morning, he approached the Mote, and had almoſt half fild it up, having made all things ready to ſtorm, and reſolved to attempt it the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with 12000. men: The beſieged having notice hereof, and finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unable to reſiſt ſo great force, made their compoſition with Turenne, and forthwith delivered up the keyes to him, upon which the French entred, and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle regarding their agreement, ſpoyled the Garriſon and kept the Soldiers priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of war; Turenne not willing to looſe time, removes with his Army further downward, and beſieged the City <hi>Rees.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Weſel,</hi> That known Fortreſſe and Magaſin of all manner of proviſion, but with a ſad ruined fortification, and unſerviceable Canon on their Walls, their Lipper-Scons much decayed, was alſo ſurrounded by Condé on the 1. of June. Aſſoon as notice came of the Enemies approach, they began with might and main to repair the fortification, but could Burgers and Soldiers together ſcarce raiſe their Breſtwork to a ſufficient height, having onely planted here and there ſome Palliſades without being beſet with Baskets; however they within did shoot ſtoutly the firſt and ſecond day, the French not anſwering them, who were very buſie in delving and making all things ready for the Battery, which the beſieged might have more invaded, if their peeces had had more force: and while they thus manfully gave fire out of <hi>Burick</hi> and <hi>Weſel,</hi> they in the Lipper Scons did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, having but 2. peeces, and both unſerviceable, and ſtanding upon a Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark not compleated, having no Palliſados yet erected, which encouraging the enemy, they 400. only in the night about the 2. and 3. of June fell upon it, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing the Watch, and quietly coming over the Wall with out let, that corner laying flat open, thus they marched to the Head-Watch, who thus ſurpriſed, they within preſently cryed for quarter, which was granted them, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they should all have been kept priſoners, but being two Companies, and almoſt as ſtrong as their aſſaulters, the moſt of them got out of the Schans into the City, one or two, who ſtood upon their defence, being shot to death. Thus this Schans was loſt, and Weſels very heart vein pricked, which the 3. dito cauſed ſo great tumult in the City, that the Citizens forſook the Wall and carried home their Armes, and would watch no more, They eſpecially the Women and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers wives requiring the delivery up of the City, and threatning ſword and hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to whomſoever withſtand it, yea they were about to lay hold on the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour by one whom they had bedaubed with ſoap for this purpoſe, intending to murder him, crying out, that ſeeing they had treacherouſly quitted the Scons, and the Canon in it, now made ſerviceable to shoot upon the City, nothing was to be expected, but it should be made a Theater of murder. The Garriſon conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of about 15. or 1600. men was to defend the outworks and thoſe within to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38464:19"/>
therefore the Captains and Councel of War deſired to deliberate about it, but Colonel van Zanten, who by reaſon of the abſence of the Governour Jucchen, had the command, would not admit the ſame, but onely treated with Major Copes, and ſome Colonels and Captains as were not well affected, and they appointed, that the Soldiery should quit the outworks, and onely keep the Poſts within, which the Citizens would no longer do. The ſame day in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, the Burgomaſters ſent a meſſenger to the Head-watch, to be let out with a Letter to Condé, which the Captain that had the watch would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto, without expreſſe order from the Commander, who agreeing thereto, the meſſenger went and returned the ſame back again with two Trumpetterss from Condé. The 4. dito, the Burgomaſters rode in a Coach with a Voeder of Rhinish-wine to the Prince, the Women ſtirred up thereto by ſome of the treacherous Captains, crying for an accord. In the mean while, the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Major, Colonels, Hoenderbeeek, Nieuland, van Haeſten, together with the Captains Inyoſta and Mengers, without calling together the Councel of War, or giving notice to the other Officers, deputed Nieuland and Mengers to go to the French Army, and privately to make agreement for the Garriſon. Oh treachery of faithleſs and effeminate Rulers and Military Officers! Thus the 5. dito, being Eaſter day, the ſubſcription was concluded to be done, and the civil and military Governours were early to be with the Prince upon pain of nullity, no ſooner the Commander was come, but Condé layes a paper before him, which he muſt forthwith, after reading, ſubſcribe, without a word contradicting: which alſo he underwrit, blotting out in that treacherous act the Luſtre of the State, and alſo herewith early before day the Enemies had the keyes delivered up to them, and before eight of the clock the Garriſon was shut up as priſoners of war in the Church, to whom, after a review of them, the Capitulation was read. Thus this invincible City was in the ſpace of 4. dayes forced without any force, leaving ſo royal a Magaſin full of Ammunition, with above a 100000. pound powder in hands of the enemy, of which, as is reported the Commiſſary Koeck was a principal inſtrument.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rees,</hi> being reaſonably well fortified, and provided with a ſufficient Scons over the Rijn, had a Garriſon of 500. men for it ſelf and Scons, This Turenne had blockt up, before the King was Maſter of Rijnberck, or Condé of Weſel, and no ſooner was the Enemy come before it, but the Scons, commaded by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain van der Hoeve was shamefully delivered up by him, who a little before had vanted of wonders he would: The Citizens knew nothing of this, till by the Canon of the Scons turned againſt the City, they were untimely warned. They within shot furiouſly, but after the loſs of Rijnberck and Weſel being more ſtrongly aſſaulted, The King ſent a Trumpetter to demand the Town, upon which the Councel of War ſent Commiſſioners empowred to treat with him: The Army being <hi>yet</hi> encamped about Weſel, and the Capitulation was ſigned in form as with them of Weſel, that the Garriſon should be 6. weeks priſoners, and after have liberty of ranſome. So this City alſo was delivered up.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>REES</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>GROLL</p>
               </figure>
               <p>When the French began to act, the Bishop of Munſter alſo after a kind of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of War ſoon ſent diverſe Troups into Twente, who ſeizing on the ſmall Towns Otmarſchen, Enſchede, Almelo, Goor, Delden, and leaving Sauvegard in them, the Bishop with his Army and ſome Troups of the Elector of Colen ſat down before the ſtrong City Groll, which without much reſiſtance gave up themſelves to the Bishop the 9. of June, whereupon the ſmall Towns thereabout were forſaken of their Garriſons, ſo as Herenberg and Borkelo alſo fell into the hands of the Bishop.</p>
               <p>This was the unhappy ſucces of the beginning of June on the Land, in which more Cities and Fortreſſes were loſt, than there paſſed dayes. In the mean while a battle fought was at Sea.</p>
               <p>After that our Fleet had often been in ſight of the English, expecting they would fall upon us, having the wind of us, yet continually turned off from us, to them; thereupon, having intelligence the English lay in Soulbay, our Fleet with a favourable winde on our approach made to them, and the 7. June early in the morning got ſight of the Enemy, and both parties ranged themſelves into three Eſquadrons, and began the fight at 8. a clock; The French who bore the white Flag, engaging with the Eſquadron of Banckert, under whom were the Zeelan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Frieſes: The Duke of York bearing the red Flag, with that of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral de Ruyter, and the blue Flag under Montague with that of van Gent. The fight was furious, and dured moſt part of the day; the advantage regaining on the ſide of the States. About noon, the whole French Eſquadron was cut off from the English Fleet, and followed by Banckert, and of both the Enemies Fleets 4 or 5. capital Ships were fired and ſunk, under which was Montagues Ship, who himſelf was drowned, and many perſons of quality ſlain. Of ours onely the Joſuah a Ship of middle ſize was loſt, and at the beginning of the fight the Admiral van Gent shot to death. The 8. dito, the English who got the wind of us, were ſeen above us, ſayling that whole day a mile loefwards, without co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to us, and evening turning quite from us, ſo as on the morrow the 9. dito, the Fleets were wholly out of ſight, upon which ours caſt Ancre before Walche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren. The French had fought little or nothing, but left the English in the brunt, and themſelves as ſoon almoſt as the Battle was well begun, drew back, and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>haps they might then have been wholly ſeparated from the English, and their after conjunction hindered, but it may be there was a particular reaſon, why ours ſo ſoon returned upon the Coaſt of Zeland, which I am not willing at preſent to enquire into my onely aime being to rehearſe the Hiſtorie of what paſſed, and not to make comments upon it: But I return again to the affairs at Land.</p>
               <p>9. June, The agreement with Rees no ſooner was ſubſcribed, but the Prince of Condé drew his Army to the Yſſel-ſide, and that very day took in Deutecom two mile from Doesburg, which ſeemed to import, that Condé intended to fall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38464:21"/>
upon the Yſſel: Turenne paſſed the ſame day by Cleef with 6000. Horſe, as far as Nimwegen, where the Prince of Orange himſelf then was, and appointed Lieutenant General Welderen for Governour of the place, and in perſon went into the works, and obſerved the motion of the enemy: and it is credible, what then was reported, that the French deſign was to ſurround Nimwegen, and ſo on the land ſide to beſiege it; and that Condé woulſt endeavour ſome way or other to break through the Yſſel: But foraſmuch as then by the treachery of Mombas, opportunity was offered to get into the Betuw, by the Tol-houſe, the former deſign was ſtopped. However it be, Condé diverted his courſe from Doesburg towards the Tol-houſe, and Turenne returned from before Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wegen, paſſing by Cleef to the Kings Army, which then was about Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merick.</p>
               <p>10. dito, Condé made an aſſault upon the Tol-houſe, for to come over the Rhijn, but was repulſed and forced to retire, and caſt up Batteries there. The Betuw was betruſted to Johan Barton of Mombas, Commiſſary General of the horſe, having by him two horſe Regiments &amp; two of Foot, with a pretended or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that in caſe the enemy should preſson, &amp; he be in danger to be driven back, by which Nimwegen alſo might be in danger, he rather should in time retire to Nimwegen, and command there: but whatever his order might be, this could not excuſe him, for himſelf acknowledgeth that the Field-marshal Wurts had the 9. dito about evening, ſent him a Letter, that his Highneſs had made van Walde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Governour of Nimwegen; and that he, the ſaid Mombas, therefore was diſcharged of that care: But that it was his Highneſs pleaſure, that he should take care of the Betuw, and that five Regiment more were a coming to him for that end: But notwithſtanding that this was order full enough to him, yet in the morning on the 10. dito, he ſent away the Foot, and cauſed the Canon to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried from his quarters, ſo that the Regiment of Horſe of Colonel Souteland was onely left to ſuſtain the aſſault of the enemy, till that Mombas meeting the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of Scot with three Companies of Painevin, the reſt of the ſuccours by his Highneſs being countermanded, becauſe of Condé's approach ſo near Does<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg, to whom Mombas ſaid that neceſſity cauſed him to retire; but yet conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the enemy now paſſed the Rhijn did not ſet upon Souteland, he with theſe and Colonel van Gent, whom they alſo met with ſome Muſquettiers, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, and then forced the enemy again to retire: But foraſmuch as Mombas doubted not, but the enemy would the next day paſſe the River, he would not ſtand to it, but reſolved to quit his Poſt, and took his way to Arnhem, and from thence to Dieren, where on then 11. dito about 9. of the clock, he came by the Prince of Orange, to the great aſtonishment of his Highneſs, who commanded the Lord Wurts thither with 2. Regiments to defend that Poſt, where he arrived toward evening, but found neither Canon nor entrenchments there.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>ARNHEM</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>SCHENCKEN SCHANS</p>
               </figure>
               <p>Before the French were got over, the Tower of the Tol-houſe, where lay a Sergeant with 18. men, was deſerted; but Turenne was no ſooner got into the Betuw, but he marched to Aarnhem, part of them running through the Betuw who the 13. dito took Heuſden and made ſpoil thereof, and from thence to Yſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oort, shooting all the afternoon upon ours who were in the Veluw, and at night rushed over the Rhijn upon the borders of the Veluw. And thus the 14. dito, being in capacity to shoot upon Aarnhem on both ſides, they within the day after, being the 15. dito made an accord early in the morning, which was ſo haſtily done, that the French entred before the Articles were once ſigned, which alſo remained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, forſooth there being no pen and inck at hand. The ſame day, Turenne was come before Knodſenburg, a ſtrong Scons and reaſonably well provided, where ſome Troups had appeared, but Turenne came not till 8. of the clock at evening, and the day after, the 16. dito in the forenoon was maſter of it, through a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous diſorder of a Drummer, and overgreat cowardiſe of the Governour, without any force done upon it. The Garriſon was permitted by Turenne to depart to Groeningen, and then preſently from the Scons fired upon Nimwegen, and the ſame day marched with his Leger to Schenckenſcons, the 16. and 17. dito ſending ſome Troups before Thiel, who gave up themſelves, and took Sauve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, which alſo was followed the 19. and 20. dito, by the impregnable Sconſes of Voren and St. Andries.</p>
               <p>It was the 17. dito, that Turenne approached by his Loopgraves, that ſtrong Fort of Schenckenſcons, wherein lay 15. Companies, which by a Trumpetter he ſummoned, and the 18. dito had it delivered up to them: A Scons on which depended the welfare of our Country, ſufficiently provided of all things requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, and with a Garriſon able to defend it, but commanded by a Rogue, who without the knowledge of the Councel of War had ſent away the Outlayers, and demolished the Forts there erected by the Lord Wurts, and ſo for mony deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up that invincible Fortreſſe.</p>
               <p>The Bishop of Munſter after the conqueſt of Groll ſate not ſtill, but maſtered Brevoort, Lochem, and what elſe was neer about; and on the 14. dito, shewed himſelf upon the plain of Deventer, to fetch away their beaſt that were graſing there; but was driven back with loſſe by the courage of ſome that iſſued out of the City upon him: But the 16. dito he came with his whole Army, aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thoſe of the Bishop of Colen, to beſiege it, The King of France alſo with the gros of his Army ſate down before Doesburg and ſummoned the ſame.</p>
               <p>If theſe firſt nine dayes were fatall to our Netherland, the following were no loſſe; eſpecially, becauſe his Highneſſe was neceſſitated to depart from the Yſſel, for Aarnem being conquered, the Veluw lay open to the Enemy, and our Army in danger of being fallen upon on all ſides, and utterly to be ruinated, ſo that his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38464:23"/>
Highneſſe having divided part of the Army, and put them in the Cities on the Yſſel under the command of Alua General for Frieſland, &amp; brought the greateſt Canons with the Ammunition and Proviſions into Doesburg, Zutphen, Deven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he with the reſt and lighter field Peeces departed thence, and coming at even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the 15. dito, before Utrecht, the gates were shut upon him, and his followers being wearied and hungry by continual marching night and day, but were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to lay without the whole night, without any refreshing. His Highneſſe deſired he might be let in, offering to defend the City, in caſe they would ſuffer it to be fortifyed, as need should require, and breaking off what was in the way; which they of Utrecht refuſed to do, requiring that the Army should lay encamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without, pretending it would be to the great damage of the Citizens, who would not be burthened by quartering of Soldiers: but at length it was agreed, that the two Regiments of the repartition of Utrecht should be admitted to come in: but the States of Holland judging, that thus doing, they should not be able to maintain that Poſt, if ſet upon, reſolved for the preſervation of Holland to beſet their Paſſes; whereupon the Leger brake up the 17. dito from Utrecht, and ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to Weeſp, Bodegrave, Goverwelle-ſluce, Schoonhoven, Gorcum, and afterward alſo Uythorn, which Poſts being now fortifyed, are found ſufficient to keep the Enemy out of Holland. The amazement, becauſe of the breaking in of the Enemy into the Betuw, and our Armies retreating was greater than I am able to relate, and the fleeing from all places to Amſterdam was unſpeakable, thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Waggons and Boats daily came in, all filled with fear and anguish.</p>
               <p>To this retreat of our Army from Utrecht, they aſcribe their damnable delivery up their City, and ſo would lay that upon others, which their own faithleſneſs and treachery brought upon themſelves. Aſſoon as the Enemy was poſſeſſed of We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, the Great ones began ſecretly to tranſport their goods, which the commons perceiving, oppoſed the ſame; yea, not without affronting the Magiſtrates them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, openly crying out to the Burgemaſters, you have ruled long enough, it is now our turn, from which tumults no good being to be expected, they ſent to the French aſſoon as Aarnem was taken, and offered their City alſo to them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring Safeguard; but they were fain to go farther, for the King yet lay before Does<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg, thus they went ſeeking the Enemy, and invited him to come, for 20. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish mile in the round not a Frenchman was to be found; Thus they of Utrecht were waiting for their Enemy, ſome of them being impatient he ſtayed ſo long: They ſet a Trumpetter upon the Tower, to give notice when the French came, which by ſound of Trumpet he did the 18. dito to ſignify to the City, and ſo to the whole Army, that the French were come into Utrecht: But it proved a miſtake, for thoſe the Trumpetter thought to be the French, were Burgers that had been ſent forth, who returning ſaw no Enemy at all.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>HINDERDAM</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>NIEUWE<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> SLUYS</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>MUY DEN</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>GOUDSE SLUYS</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>NIEWER BRUGH</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>PAIN ET VIN</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>WIERICKE</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>DEVENTER</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>DOESBURH</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>AEN DEN</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>ISEL</p>
               </figure>
               <p>The 20. dito, Safeguard from the King came in with two Trumpetters, and ſoon after a French Garriſon: whereupon they preſently Capitulate for the whole Province, a thing never heard before, and cauſe of all ſubſequent diſaſter. For hereby Over-Yſſel pretended to be cut off from Holland, ſo follows the example of Utrecht and make Capitulations alſo, a project alſo to do the ſame being made ready in Frieſland; yea, Holland it ſelf almoſt gone, moſt of the Cities ſpeak of ſending for Safeguard, and they in higheſt place knew no better remedy; all this came from Utrecht, Overyſſel following their example, and had not Providence appeared for us in a wonderfull and unexpected way, we had all been delivered up to the fury of the Enemy.</p>
               <p>The 16. July, the Bishop of Munſter came before Deventer, a gallant fortified City provided of all things with a ſtrong garriſon of Soldiers, beſides 1450. South-Holland Countrymen &amp; reſolute Citizens together, making up 10000. able men, all reſolved to ſtand out to the utmoſt againſt the Enemy. The Colonel Stecke was Commander in chief over the Garriſon, as alſo Head of the provintial Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia: He held much communication with the Governour of Coeverden Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel Boerſma, whom his Highneſs not truſting, had cauſed to come to Deventer, where he thought, he could do no great hurt. The Enemy marched over the Yſſel, where was moſt convenience behind the hedges of the city gardens, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and plant his morter peeces, out of which the 20. early in the morning he shot into the City with Bombes, doing little or no harm with them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Commander for to ſatisfie the Citizens, offered to make a ſally upon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38464:27"/>
the Enemy, as alſo he did, not altogether without ſucceſſe; yet ſo purpoſely ordered, as not to do to much hurt to the Enemy. In the mean while, they continued the Bombes from the overſide of the Yſſel till the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, when ſome of the Magiſtrates without the knowledge of the Citizens or Garriſon, ſent a Letter to the Bishop, deſiring a ceſſation of Armes, and ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct for Committees to go fetch the advice of the Cities Campen and Swol; this was done after that the Bishop the day before had notifyed, that his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention was to joyn Deventer again to the Empire. And the 21. in the morning they ſent again a Trumpetter, for ceſſation of Arms, the Canons ſounding too loud in their ears, though they hitherto haſt ſuſtained little harm by them. Now they called the ſworn Commons, where by the moſt voyces it was concluded to give over the City, and three were deputed to capitulate, the Citizens and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers knowing nothing thereof, ſave the Governour inſligated by that Traytor Boerſma. In the mean while, upon pain of death, no man might shoot, and the Soldiers who were on flame to ruine the Enemies approches and Batteries, were not ſuffered to fall on. Toward evening the agreement was made without the knowledge of the Councel of War, and with a damnable ſecluding of the Soldie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who all, the very Peſants included, were by this horrid accord to remain pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners of war, and be shut up in the Churches. The 21. dito, late in the night, the City was poſſeſſed by the enemy, none almoſt knowing thereof, or any neceſſity preſſing thereunto, ſave onely the treachery of theſe wicked Gueſts.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>SWOL</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>CAMPEN</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>SUTPHEN</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>DOESBERGH</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>SCHANS aut HEEREVEEN</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>BL<hi rend="sup">E</hi>SSER BRUGH</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>STOCKSTER HORN</p>
               </figure>
               <p>17. June, The King of France was come before Doesburg, and though there were a reaſonable ſtrong Garriſon in it, yet without any great reſiſtance, they gave up themſelves to the King, who from thence in haſte went to Zutphen, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it in without trouble, though it were alſo provided reaſonably well of all things, and a Garriſon in it: In both theſe Cities the Soldiery and alſo the Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands Waart-gelders or Auxiliary Troups, were detained priſoners of war. Thu<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there being no more to be conquered at the Yſſel; the King brake up from thence, and came in Perſon with his Army the 27. dito paſt Aarnem hard by Utrecht, encamping himſelf without the City, and put Garriſons in all the Cities of that Province, as Wijck, Montfoort, Ouwater, Yſelſteyn, Amersfoort, and the Gelder Cities, Harderwijck and Elburg; yea, in Woerden it ſelf a City in Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and ſome few coming before Naarden, the dread was ſo great, that they within caſt away their Arms, ſome ſwimming over the Mote of the City, leaving it for the French to poſſeſs: Muyen alſo was gone, taken in by fifteen men, but were again driven out: Theſe Succeſſes ſo tranſported the French, that ſome few of them asked the way to Amſterdam, as thinking to take in that alſo. The King remained in the Leger without Utrecht, &amp; came the 5. July accompanied with Duke d'Orleans, Monmouth, Luxenburg, and other Grandees, to take a view of the Town, being on Horſeback, but ſoon returned out again into the Leger; appointing the Duke of Luxenburg Governour of the City and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and Stoupa General of the Switzers, Commander of the City. But we will leave the King here a while, Turenne before Nimwegen, and the Bishop of Munſter in Over-Yſſel; for to take notice, what fell out worth the obſervation about that time, both in the Politicks and the Militia, and ſo make progreſſe in what was acted by the enemy.</p>
               <p>It was a ſmall thing to looſe Cities and Forts, whole Provinces together giving up themſelves to the enemy. And though it ſeemeth ridiculous, that ſome of the French would know the way to Amſterdam to go and take it in; yet I verily believe, that if at that time 4. or 5000. horſe onely had gone forward, Amſterdam it ſelf and thereby Holland; yea, the whole State would have fallen into the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hand, ſo great terrour had ſeized upon all, &amp; the Regents voyd of Counſel: The Magiſtrates in their common Councel diſputing, whither they should quit all, or endeavour a while to defend themſelves: Many pretending that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, as not being provided with neceſſaries, wherefore their Counſel was in caſe the Enemy came, to meet him with the Keyes: Others would that Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks should be erected, bridges broken down; ſcarce knowing what they ſaid or did, ſetting many times the cart before the horſe. I dread even to think upon
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38464:31"/>
the terrour and aſtonishment of that time, eſpecially of the 25. June and there about, the moſt underſtanding of the Land then being at non-plus: The Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionary himſelf, who ſeldom or never was at a pinch, plucking up his shoulders, and is ſaid to have given no other advice than a good and ſpeedy accommodation with the Enemy, as the onely expedient to be found: In proſecution of which advice three Deputies were ſuddenly ſent for England, and three to the French Leger, of whom the Lord d'Groot was the chief. I know not what inſtructions they had, but it is ſaid, that they for England had no other Commiſſion, than to learn what the demand of that King was, and that they for the French Leger had full power to treat with the King; that is, to deliver up the Country, for in that conjuncture of time, what elſe could be expected than an honorable capitulation.</p>
               <p>But the Province of Zealand, June 29. rejected the reaſons alledged by Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land for this Commiſſion, and proteſted againſt them, declaring it to be a thing unheard of in the government of theſe Countries, to make any Plenipotentiaries (without an arreſted inſtruction) to treat with any Potentate, much leſſe with an open Enemy; eſpecially when it concerned our Religion, Liberty and the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full government of the Land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherefore they diſavowed this Commiſſion, as ſuſpicious and of dangerous conſequence.</p>
               <p>The Communalty, now taking notice of theſe tranſactions, and ſeeing the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments of the Regents, and the thteatned danger, begin to raiſe tumults: Others flee where ever they imagine a place of ſafety to be, transſporting their families, and what was moſt precious Eaſt, Weſt, to France, yea England it ſelf, tranſporting an ineſtimable Treaſure out of the Country to their extream dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and damage; the remaining with trembling ſpirits, at laſt take up Arms to defend their Country: The Magiſtracy in diverſe Cities being fain, as if they were willing to animate and encourage the reſt, to contribute for defence of their Cities, other places in the mean while wholy neglected; but the Poſts for Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands ſecurity were beſet with Soldiers, and made defenſible, the Banks and Dams about Amſterdam opened, the Country ſet under water, the wayes cut throw, bridges caſt down, Trenchments erected, Out-layers brought upon the Rivers, the Wall repaired, Canon brought up, the Watch doubbled, and for ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Citizens, the 29. of June it was published from the Town-houſe, that the Councel was fully reſolved to defend the City to the utmoſt; and burgers were ſent out of the Hague and Rotterdam to the Poſts of the Army, and out of other Cities to the Frontiers of Holland, Heuſden, Geertruydenburg, Breda, the Klundert, the Briel, &amp;c. But all this could not take away from the diſturbed ſpirits of men, that impreſſion they had taken that many members of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy were guilty of treaſon, and held correſpondence with the enemy, as often it happens, the bad ſucceſſe of undertakings is laid to the charge of the managers thereof.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of Holland</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>25. dito, They of Aardenberg in Vlaenders got tidings, that the French out of their quarters at Cortrijck and thereabouts, had gathered many men for to aſſault them, at which very time Captain <hi>Cauw</hi> Commander of Aardenberg, perhaps being not ignorant of the exploit, was gone for Zeeland: Whereupon the Garriſon onely conſiſting of 73. men, and 165. citizens were put into po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture by the vigilant direction of Enſign <hi>Beeckman,</hi> as much as poſſibly he could. At night about 11. of the clock the French approached being 4000. Horſe and Foot, and by a Trumpetter ſummoned the City, which after refuſal they fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by force; but by the magnanimity of thoſe few within they were ſo manfully repulſed, that after three hours ſtorming, they were forced with great loſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the morning to draw off, retiring out of Canon shot: and they of Aarden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg the 26. dito, got 60. men for ſuccour with ſome Ammunition, whereupon the Enemy ſtrengthened with 2000. more fell on again furiouſly, at one a clock at night, their Foot being driven on by the Horſe advancing, (though moſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reſiſting by them in the City) to the very walls &amp; maſtered a Ravelin before the Gate, the Fall-bridge of the inner-gate let down, when happily at that very nick of time Colonel Spindler came to aſſiſt them with 150. men, which ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed their courage and ſtrength, that the Enemy was forced again to retire: They of the Enemy who were got into the Raveling being amazed, becauſe of the hot shooting, and of the bridge, which they muſt paſſe over, called for quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which was not granted before they had caſt their weapons from them, and drawing up the outmoſt Fall-bridge, they were brought in, the reſt eſcaping from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38464:33"/>
whence they were come. The way round about was ſtrawed with the ſlain, being to the number of a 1000. beſides 200. wounded, whom they carried along with them, not one being ſlain in the City, and 1. or 2. onely wounded: The priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were, 1. Colonel, 2. Lieutenants Colonels, 28. Captains and Lieutenants, 530. common ſoldiers; a glorious victory for this Place, which should have been, according to former reſolution, demolished as not tenable, but now hath deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved better Walls than Utrecht, and ſuch as they: for although their walls were not defenſible, and the moat not 3. foot deep, yet the magnanimity of the citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens was their ſtrength, yea every woman and maid, to the very children them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves did ſervice, as ſoldiers, ſupplying the defect of bullets with their shop waites, broken pots and the like. Oh, had things been thus carried in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, our Netherlands had not ſo shamely loſt their renown.</p>
               <p>29. dito, <hi>Jacob de Graaf</hi> was condemned to be executed by the ſword, for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulting the <hi>Penſionaris de Wit,</hi> (though his wounds were not perillous at all as to death) as having committed <hi>Crimen Laeſae Majeſtatis,</hi> being brought to execution. the gates of the Cities near about were kept shut up, and all the wayes beſet with Horſe, ſo that this work, notwithſtanding the Executioner made divers blows before he could cut off his Head, was accomplished without any great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>T<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>SAS VAN GENT</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>AERDENBURG</p>
               </figure>
               <p>But for all this, the ſpirits of the people were not appeaſed, they ſaw the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment remained in their hands, againſt whoſe will and endeavour, his Highneſſe was eſtablished, who they thought would not ceaſe, aſmuch as might to counter mine his Highneſſe, and for to prevent their own fall, would preſume to plot his fall though to the ruine of the State: They ſaw that the power deferred on his Highneſſe, was fruitleſs without liberty to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the ſame, They ſaw the ſame management of affairs, were yet as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; therefore they would have an alteration of the Government, and foraſmuch as for ſome years paſt the Magiſtrates of moſt Cities in Holland were brought in by the direction of Penſionaris <hi>de Wit,</hi> that few other which were not of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, were admitted to the Government; therefore the Communalty would have theſe removed, terming them the States Party, <hi>Cabal</hi> of de <hi>Wit</hi> and faction of <hi>Louveſtein</hi>; yea, ſome ſaid plainly they were Traytors of the Land, of whom they ſaid, the Penſionaris and his brother were Head, together with the Ambaſſador <hi>de Groot,</hi> and ſome other; Inſomuch that the Penſionaris com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in a Letter to his Highneſſe 11. July of Pamphlets againſt him, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38464:35"/>
in ſpecial that he was accuſed to have managed the ſecret correſpondence-treaſure unfaithfully, and not to have taken due care for the Armies of the State: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Highneſſe anſwered dito 22. that ſuch Pamphlets were not to be regarded, that himſelf was fain to ſuffer the like licentouſneſſe againſt him; That of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret correſpondence money he knew nothing, but that the Lords Councellers of the Commiſſion were to be witneſſes thereof: and that by reaſon of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of affairs he could not ſpecify what defects of the Armies had been, nor what ſupply had from time to time been made, directing for his deſired juſtification to the actions of his carefull performance therein.</p>
               <p>In Zeeland many of the Lords alſo were ſaid to follow the party of <hi>de Wit</hi>: whereupon a general riſing was on a ſudden throughout whole Holland and Zeeland, ſome they aſſailed in perſon, others had their houſes ſpoiled, many were forced to quit their places in Government; yea, in ſome places all the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates put by; ſome Cities were by force of the Peſants taken in, and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates conſtrained to act according to their wil, which confuſion preſaging the unavoidable ruine of the Country, cauſed the States to reſolve Auguſt 27. not onely to empower his Highneſs, according as should be requiſite and his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure should be, to alter the Magiſtracy in all Cities, but alſo entreated him for the common good, to do it with all ſpeed.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>OUDE SCHANS</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>COEVENDEN</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>NIEWE SCHANS</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>de BOUR TANGE</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>GRAAF</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>GENNEPE HUYS</p>
               </figure>
               <p>Turenne, after the taking of Schenckenſconſe, was again come before Nimwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen; but in the mean while, our Soldiers had quitted the ſtrong <hi>Houſe te Gennip,</hi> and the Garriſon being 4. Companies marched to Nimwegen, and the 7. and 28. June, our Horſe of Nimwegen went with 64. Carts to fetch thence 84. barrels of powder, bullets, and match, with ſome laſts of Rie, intending with a ſecond Convoy to bring away the reſt into Nimwegen: upon whom the French shot very hard out of Knotſenburg, and 2 Batteries they had made, caſting alſo many Fire-bullets and Granados of 90. &amp; 100. pound weight, by which three Out-layers before Nimwegen were: But they within were not behind hand with them: ſo that the French the 2. and 3. July paſſed the Waal by their Ship-bridge, and rounded the City on the Land-ſide, bringing their Loop-graves as in an inſtant to the Moat, and the 4 dito made a Battery with 5. half Kartouwen, and aſſaulted by ſtorm that night the Peſthouſe-bulwark, entring the ſame, but were driven out again, the Colonel <hi>van Gent,</hi> brother of the Admiral deceaſed, being there ſlain: The 6. dito in the night they ſtormed again, but were three times coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly beaten off, as alſo the 7. dito. In the mean while, Patents were come to the <hi>Grave,</hi> to depart with moſt part of the Garriſon to the <hi>Bos,</hi> where the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour having gotten in ſome Spaniards, but no order to receive them, ſent them back to the <hi>Grave,</hi> where being come near the City, they were ſet upon by the French, and for the moſt part routed, by which alſo the <hi>Grave</hi> was loſt. By this time, the French before Nimwegen were advanced with their works to the Borſt-werings, and already undermined two Bulwarks: whereupon the 8. dito they began to parly, and the 9. dito the agreement was made, that the Garriſon conſiſting of 7. Companies of Horſe, and about 40. Foot, with one Company Waartgelders from the Briel, should all remain priſoners of War, excepting five Companies of Utrecht citizens, and of Rhenen and Montfoort, who marched out free with their Arms<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What the reaſon was, this City did ſo haſtily and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out more conſtraint give up to the Enemy, is diverſly judged of, and it is ſaid that the loſſe of the <hi>Grave</hi> was a thing plotted aforehand.</p>
               <p>Then 11. July, Turenne from Nimwegen went to the Grave, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from thence to the Bos, which wanting all things, ſent Deputies to his Highneſs, who well knowing what concernment the Bos was of, was fain to give this anſwer, that he was ſorry he could not help them, having no more power, than they to do it: yet at length, becauſe of the great importance of the place, ſome Canons and Ammunition were ſent by Ships thither; but coming therewith to Gorcum, they had the tidings that Creveceur was loſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not poſſible to bring it to the Bos: Therefore the Field-marshal Wurts commanding there, unladed the Canon to uſe then for the defence of Gorcum. They of the Bos had quitted the Sconſes Engelen and Orten, and brought the Canon into the City, with all which they had ſcarcely enough to defend the Brill
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38464:39"/>
as was requiſite, the Garriſon alſo was but weak: The 13. July, they ſaw the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my at Ulymen, and part marching to Engelen and Crevecoeur, the firſt of which they put forces into, and beſieging the other with many more, after two dayes shooting on it, became conquerors thereof; the gros of the Leger laying at Box<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel and the Vugt, above 20000. ſtrong.</p>
               <p>The 11. July, the King brake up with his Army from Utrecht, lodging that night in the Grep, and arrived the 12. dito to Aarnem, drawing forth the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Woerden and Ouwater to Utrecht, they of Ouwater being purſued by ſome of the Earl of Horns quarters, and ſome taken priſoners, beſides a good booty of Money and Arms. The King having given a viſit to the Prince of Condé, and Duke d' Auguin, both lying very weak at Aarnem; departed thence the 13. dito to the Betuw, ſending part of his Army to Bommel, ſoon maſtering it, forthwith putting forces into the ſmaller Towns, Heucklon, Aſperen and Leerdam: The 14. dito, the King marched over the Bridge by Nimwegen to the Grave, and arrived the 16. dito in his Leger before the Bos, being in perſon the 21. dito at Vugt, from whence he betook himſelf again to Boxel.</p>
               <p>Not onely the Netherlands, but all Chriſtendom ſtood aſtonished to ſee the Enemy already approached within two dutch miles of Amſterdam, There keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Poſt, having in ſo short a time conquered ſo great a number of Cities and Forts.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="list_of_losses">
                           <head>A Liſt of the Cities and Forts conquered by the Enemy, ſince the 1. of June to the 19. Iuly.</head>
                           <list>
                              <head>In the Dukedom Cleef.</head>
                              <item>Orſoy.</item>
                              <item>Rhijnberck.</item>
                              <item>Burick.</item>
                              <item>Weſel, and the Lippe-Sconſe.</item>
                              <item>Rees and the Sconſe.</item>
                              <item>Emmerick.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>In the County of Groe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningen.</head>
                              <item>Winſchoten.</item>
                              <item>Oude Sconſe.</item>
                              <item>Boonder Sconſe.</item>
                              <item>New Sconſe.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>In Eaſt-Frieſland, and Frieſland.</head>
                              <item>d'Eyler Sconſe.</item>
                              <item>Slijkenburg or Kuinder</item>
                              <item>Sconſe.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>In Gelderland.</head>
                              <item>Spijckfoort.</item>
                              <item>Schencken Sconſe.</item>
                              <item>Tol-houſe.</item>
                              <item>Yſſeloort.</item>
                              <item>Hattem.</item>
                              <item>Elbrug.</item>
                              <item>Harderwijck.</item>
                              <item>Aarnhem.</item>
                              <item>Wageningen.</item>
                              <item>Knotſenburg.</item>
                              <item>Nimwegen.</item>
                              <item>Grave.</item>
                              <item>Tiel.</item>
                              <item>Bommel.</item>
                              <item>Sconſe te Vooren.</item>
                              <item>Sconſe St. Andrews.</item>
                              <item>The Retrenchment of the Yſſel.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>In Brabant.</head>
                              <item>Crevecoeur.</item>
                              <item>Sconſe te Engelen.</item>
                              <item>Orte-Sconſe.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>In the County Zutphen.</head>
                              <item>Yſſelburg.</item>
                              <item>Anholt.</item>
                              <item>'s Heeren-berg.</item>
                              <item>Zevenaar.</item>
                              <item>Heuſſen.</item>
                              <item>Dotechem.</item>
                              <item>Brevoort.</item>
                              <item>Grolle.</item>
                              <item>Lochem.</item>
                              <item>Doesburg.</item>
                              <item>Zutphen.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>In Over-Yſſel.</head>
                              <item>Deventer.</item>
                              <item>Hardenberg.</item>
                              <item>Ommer Sconſe.</item>
                              <item>Rouveen Sconſe.</item>
                              <item>Zwoll, and the retrech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:38464:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:38464:40"/>
                                 <figure>
                                    <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                                    <p>NIMMEGEN</p>
                                 </figure>
                                 <figure>
                                    <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                                    <p>SCHANS de VORN</p>
                                 </figure>
                                 <figure>
                                    <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                                    <p>SCHANS S. ANDRIES</p>
                                 </figure>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:38464:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                                 <figure>
                                    <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                                    <p>BOMMEL</p>
                                 </figure>
                                 <figure>
                                    <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                                    <p>CREVECEUR</p>
                                 </figure>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:38464:41"/>
                                 <pb n="33" facs="tcp:38464:41"/>
with three Sconſes.</item>
                              <item>Campen with the Scons.</item>
                              <item>Haſſelt.</item>
                              <item>Swartſluce.</item>
                              <item>Geelmuyen.</item>
                              <item>Fullenhove.</item>
                              <item>Blockzijl.</item>
                              <item>Steenwijck.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>In the Drente.</head>
                              <item>Meppel.</item>
                              <item>Coeverden.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>In the Twente.</head>
                              <item>Enſchede.</item>
                              <item>Oldenzeel.</item>
                              <item>Degnecham.</item>
                              <item>Almelo.</item>
                              <item>Delden.</item>
                              <item>Goor.</item>
                              <item>Diepenhem.</item>
                              <item>Rijſſen.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>In Utrecht Province.</head>
                              <item>Rhenen.</item>
                              <item>Wijck te Duurſtee.</item>
                              <item>Amersfoort.</item>
                              <item>Utrecht.</item>
                              <item>Ouwater.</item>
                              <item>Yſſelſtein.</item>
                              <item>Montfoort.</item>
                           </list>
                           <list>
                              <head>In Holland.</head>
                              <item>Buuren.</item>
                              <item>Kuylenburg.</item>
                              <item>Vyanen.</item>
                              <item>Heucklom.</item>
                              <item>Leerdam.</item>
                              <item>Aſperen.</item>
                              <item>Woerden.</item>
                              <item>Naarden.</item>
                           </list>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>The Province of Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land onely being free wholy from them.</p>
               <p>England it ſelf was jealous becauſe of theſe ſucceſſes, unwilling that France should become Maſter of all, thinking it therefore high time to ſee how the work lay, and ſpeedily ſent Buckingham, Arlington, and Hallifax as Plenipotentiaries to the King of France, with a Commiſſion dated 31. June. Theſe Lords arrived at the Hague 4. July, and departed the day after to the Army of his Highneſſe at Bodegrave, without further declaring themſelves, except in exorbitant demands. The 6. dito in the afternoon, they departed from the Princes Leger to the King of France, who yet lay encamped before Utrecht, and followed the French Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the Bos, being every where nobly entertained, and complimented: Where they the 16 dito renewed their treaty of Alliance; thereby more nearly binding themſelves to hearken to no propoſitions of Peace, but with knowledge on both ſides, and to come to no agreement, but with the ſatisfaction of both, of which notice was to be given to the States by their Deputies, as alſo by a Letter of the English Plenipotentiaries was done from Boxtel dito 17. the ſame being communicated to his Highneſs, with an annex of the Articles, upon which they might have peace.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="demands">
                           <head>Demands and Conditions on which his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty would make Peace with the States General of the United Provinces.</head>
                           <p>THat the Proclamations formerly put forth by the States General, forbidding the French Wines and Brandewine, with all the impoſitions upon French Wares and Manufactures, be revoked: That within <hi>3.</hi> months a Treaty of Commerce between his Majeſty and the ſaid States shall be concluded, wherein alſo shall be comprehended the regulating of the French and Holland Eaſt and Weſt Indies Companies.</p>
                           <p n="2">
                              <hi>2.</hi> That for the future, throughout all the United Provinces not onely a full liberty; But alſo shall the publick exerciſe of the Romish Catholick, Apoſtolical Religion: ſo that in all places, where more than one Church shall be, one be given over to the Catholicks: To whom alſo it shall be permitted to build one where there is none, and they shall have liberty untill ſuch time as the Church shal be built, openly to celebrate Divine ſervice in ſuch houſes as they shall to that end buy
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38464:42"/>
or hire. That by the States General, or every Province in particular, a reaſonable main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance out of the Goods which have formerly belonged to the Church, or ſuch like, be allotted to the Paſtor or Prieſt in every of the ſaid Churches.</p>
                           <p n="3">
                              <hi>3.</hi> And foraſmuch as the Deputies of the ſaid States ſent to his Majeſty, have for ſpecial rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons deſired, that it would pleaſe him by the Peace to permit the Body of the United Netherlands to remain in the State, ſo as hitherto it hath been, and thereupon in change to give unto his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty for the Conqueſts, wherewith it hath pleaſed God to bleſſe his juſt War, they have offered to him in ſtead of the Provinces, Cities and Places which his Majeſty already poſſeſſeth, to quit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him other Lands, Cities and Places, which in Brabant and Flanders by the Spaniard have been delivered up to them: His Majeſty although he be now Maſter of three whole of the <hi>7.</hi> Provinces in the United Netherlands, together with ſome of the Places and Poſts in Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, hath willed for to preſerve the ſaid ſeven Provinces in their firſt Union, to reſtore unto them what by his forces he hath poſeſſed himſelf of in the ſaid Provinces, excepting what here under shall be ſpecified and upon the following conditions.</p>
                           <p n="4">
                              <hi>4.</hi> That the ſaid States shall quit unto his Majeſty generally all the Provinces, Cities and Places, which they have in Flanders and Brabant, and thoſe that have been quitted to them by the Spaniard, onely excepting Sluce and the Iland of Caſant.</p>
                           <p n="5">
                              <hi>5.</hi> The ſaid States alſo shall quit to his Majeſty the City <hi>Nimwegen</hi> with the depencdencies and all belonging to it, The Fort Knotſenburg, Schenckenſcons, and the part of the Province of Gelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, lying on this ſide the Rhijn, as to France, together with the whole Iſland of Bommel, the Iſland and Fort of Voorne, the Fort St. Andries, and the Caſtle of Louveſtein, and the Fort Crevecoeur.</p>
                           <p n="6">
                              <hi>6.</hi> The ſaid States alſo shall quit to his Majeſty Grave, with its dependencies and all belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, and shall give unto him the propriety of the City, and the County Meurs, to diſpoſe thereof according to his pleaſure, with condition that the ſaid States shall indemnifie the Prince of Orange as to the ſaid County, and other Places, Cities and Countries belonging to the ſaid Prince, but yeelded up to his Majeſty.</p>
                           <p n="7">
                              <hi>7.</hi> That the ſaid States shall yeeld to his Majeſty all ſuch claim as they may have had or could pretend unto, in thoſe places which his Majeſty hath taken from the ſaid States in the Empire, that alſo they yeeld the ſame in favour of the Prince and Earl of Eaſt Frieſland, of all ſuch claims as they have or may pretend, unto in ſuch Places as they poſſeſſe in his Land; as namely, the City Embden, The Sconſe van Leer-oort, and the Ylerſconſe, out of which they shall recall their Garriſons.</p>
                           <p n="8">
                              <hi>8.</hi> That alſo it shall be permitted to the Subjects of his Majeſty, in all thoſe Countries, Cities and Places of the States General, which have been yielded up to his Majeſty to go in and out both by Water and by Land, Rivers and Streams, without paying any due or impoſition, or be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be viſited, as to their goods, bagage, munition of war, and proviſion what ſoever.</p>
                           <p n="9">
                              <hi>9.</hi> The ſaid States shall oblige themſelves to the Order and Religion of Malta, to cauſe to be reſtored unto the ſaid Order all the Rights, which shall be found belonging unto them.</p>
                           <p n="10">
                              <hi>10.</hi> The ſaid States shall promiſe to cauſe the Children of the Earl of Bentem to be reſtored to him, which by the authority and protection of the ſaid States, are by the Counteſſe, wife of the Earl of Bentem, detained from him, notwithſtanding his often requeſting the ſame; thereto alſo obtaining the Letters of the Emperor, and of his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, for the reſtoring of them.</p>
                           <p n="11">
                              <hi>11.</hi> The ſaid States shall promiſe to indemnifie his Majeſty of part of the exceſſive Charges he hath been neceſſitated to in this War, and pay unto him within the time that shall be agreed upon, the ſome of <hi>20.</hi> millions, and then his Majeſty will acquit them of the three millions, with all the intreſt thereof, which they owe unto his Majeſty for the ſaid ſum, his Majeſties Father of happy memory, had lent unto them Anno <hi>1651.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="12">
                              <pb n="35" facs="tcp:38464:42"/>
                              <hi>12.</hi> That in acknowledgment of the Peace, which his Majeſty is willing then to grant unto them, when he could have made his Conqueſts further in their Country; The ſaid States hall every year by an Ambaſſador Extraordinary upon a certain ſtipulated day, cauſe to be preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him a Golden Medal weighing a mark, which shall contain; that they hold the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame Freedom from his Majeſty, which the Kings his Predeceſſors have helped them to obtain.</p>
                           <p n="13">
                              <hi>13.</hi> That although his Majeſty doth declare to content himſelf with the foreſaid Conditions, in caſe they be accepted within <hi>10.</hi> dayes, after which his Majeſty pretendeth to bee no longer obliged thereto; nevertheleſſe, herewith he gives to wit, that although the ſame should be owned by the States, they shall not be of any force, and that his Majeſty will enter upon no Treaty of Ceſſation or of Peace, before ſuch time as the King of England on his account shall receive ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction from the ſaid States, and that the Princes of the Empire allied with his Majeſty in this war shall likewiſe be content with the Condition, that shall by the States be offered unto them.</p>
                           <div type="commentary">
                              <head>Here followeth a further Amplication of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Articles.</head>
                              <p>ANd that it may appear by the choyce of more Conditions than one, how uprightly his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty had been pleaſed to preſent to the ſaid States General, divers wayes for to obtain the Peace they deſired of him, and not to bring ſo far as was in his power the pretences, which he juſtly might by force of Arms, and the continuance of his Victories; Therefore his Majeſty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, that without ſtanding, preciſely to the offers which here before have by the ſaid States been made, as alſo the Conditions which by form of alternative he had required of them, He will content himſelf with keeping all the Conqueſts, his Majeſty at preſent poſſeſſeth, together of thoſe he may further Conquer, untill that the ſaid States shall have conſented to theſe Conditions; to wit, the whole Province and Dukedom of Gelderland belonging to the States, the Province of Utrecht and County Zutphen, all the Cities, Places and Fortreſſes, which are in the ſaid Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces their appendencies, and what belongeth to them without exception; the Soveraignties of the Provinces, Lands, Cities and Places conquered by his Majeſty with the appendencies and all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereto, to remain for the future for ever to his Majeſty.</p>
                              <p>And to the end, the ſaid Conqueſts, Countries and Places delivered up to his Majeſty, may the better be brought to a capacity, through the aſſiſtance of the Empire to be ſtrenthened; the ſaid States shall renounce all Soveragnity over the Cities Maſtricht and the Wijcke, as alſo of what they now hold in Overmaſe, Dalen, Fouquemont, and the Country belonging to the Bos, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the City and Meyerije of the ſaid Bos, and all what belongeth to the appendices thereof, with the Fort Crevecoeur.</p>
                              <p>And that the Treaty upon the laſt Terms might ſerve, not onely to re-eſtablish the friendships and alliance between his Majeſty and the ſaid States, but to procure the reſt and tranquility of the Empire, which his Majeſty as Guardian and conſerver of the Treaties of Weſtphalia, doth in ſpeciall lay to heart, his Majeſty will promiſe, after the Peace made, to renounce in favour to the Princes of the Empire, to all that right which by law of Armes may appertain unto him, as to thoſe Places which his Majeſty hath taken from the States in the precinct of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, his Majeſty reſerving onely to himſelf the liberty to demolish the fortification thereof.</p>
                              <p>
                                 <pb n="36" facs="tcp:38464:43"/>But foraſmuch as his Majeſty will of himſelf contribute to re-eſtablis the Princes of the Empire in the free poſſeſſion of the Cities and Places belonging to them; therefore he hath alſo willed to procure, that the ſaid States General shall draw forth their Garriſons out of the Cities &amp; Places, which they hold as yet in the Empire; namely the City Embden, the Fort of Leer-oort, and Iler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſconſe, which shall be delivered up to the Prince and Earl of Eaſt-Frieſland, with all the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges appertaining in reſpect of the ſaid County: and to the end that the needfull correſpondence between France &amp; the City Maeſtricht (which is to be given up to his Majeſty) may be for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture no occaſion of Conteſt, It shall be by both parties eſtipulated, to endeavour a grounded and free paſſage for the Troups of his Majeſty from the French Frontiers to the ſaid Maeſtricht, from the Elector of Ceulen, as Prince and Bishop of Luyck, yet upon condition, not to make uſe of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, but with paying what charges they are at, that the Country be not burthened.</p>
                              <p>Furthermore, the Articles mentioned in the former notition, shall remain in full as they are, even that concerning the quitting of the City and County Meurs, onely excepting thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the delivery up of other Lands and Places, to be made by the ſaid States to his Majeſty.</p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div type="demands">
                           <head>Demands and Conditions, upon which the King of England would conſent to make Peace with the States General of the United Provinces.</head>
                           <p n="1">1. <hi>THe King of England underſtands, that the Hollanders without any gainfaying shall give unto him the honor of the Flag, yea, ſo as their whole Fleet shall ſtrike, and let fall their Top-ſail for any one English Ship, bearing the Flag of his Majeſty throughout the whole British Sea, even to the Coaſts of Holland.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="2">2. <hi>Free permiſſion for a whole year to all English that remained in the Colony of Surinam, to depart thence when they shall deſire, with all their goods, of what nature ſoever they be, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Treaty of Breda.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="3">3. <hi>Perpetual banishment out of all the Territories of the United Provinces of all the Kings Subjects that are declared guilty of Crimen Laeſae Majeſtatis, together with all other, which shall be noted by his Majeſty to have published ſeditious Libels, or otherwiſe to have conſpired againſt the Peace, and tranquility of his Kingdoms.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="4">4. <hi>Reſtoring to his Majeſty the expences of the war, to the ſum of one million of pounds ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, whereof</hi> 400000. <hi>shall be paid, between this and the month October next enſuing, and the reſt by</hi> 400000. <hi>pounds ſterling every year.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="5">5. <hi>A yearly pay for ever of</hi> 10000 <hi>pounds ſterling, for the grant they shall have from the King to catch Herrings upon the Coaſts of England, Scotland and Yreland.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="6">6. <hi>The preſent Prince of Orange and his Succeſſors, shall have the Souveragnity of the United Netherlands, excepting of what shall fall to the share of the Two Kings and their Allies, or shall at leaſt enjoy for ever the honour of Admiral General, and Stadtholder in the higheſt degree, that hath by the foregoing Princes been enjoyed.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="7">7. <hi>That within three moneths after the Peace, a Treaty of Commerce shall be made, as well to the regulating of Trade in India, according to demands formerly made, as to the advance of the Subjects of his Majeſty in their trading, going, coming or habituating in any of the Countries belonging to the ſaid States, and with ſuch advantagious conditions, as are agreed unto the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions moſt in favour.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="8">8. <hi>The Iſland of Walcheren, the City and Caſtle of Sluce with its dependencies, the Iſland of Caſſant, that of Goeree, and the Iſland of Voorne shall be put into the hands of his Majeſty by way of Caution, for the performing of the Conditions before ſpecified.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="9">9. <hi>And however his Majeſty declareth to content himſelf with the foreſaid Conditions, in caſe the ſame be within ten dayes accepted, after which his Majeſty underſtands himſelf no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er obliged; Nevertheleſs, he doth peremtorily declare, that although the ſaid States should ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them, yet they shall be of no force, nor that his Majeſty will make any Treaty of Peace or Ceſſation, before ſuch time as the moſt Chriſtian King shall in his regard by the ſaid States have received ſatisfaction, as alſo that the Princes of the Empire allied with his Majeſty in this War, shall be contented with the Conditions preſented to them by the ſaid States.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:38464:43"/>I believe there will few be found that do imagine ſuch an unreaſonable project to proceed from ſuch prudent royal Councels, and nevertheleſs it pleaſed thoſe Lords to riſe thus high, perhaps not well adviſed that the Holland generoſity (though at preſent much brougt under) was yet too great, thus willingly to ſubject them ſelfs to the arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cruelty of the French, &amp; inſupportable yoke of the English.</p>
               <p>The 19. dito, the English Ambaſſadors came in the Kings own coach, conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by 500. horſe to Antwerp, where they had conference with the Earl of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, having a Commiſſioner of France with them, labouring with all their might to draw Montery from ſiding with us, foraſmuch as hitherto, not onely by order from the Spanish Court, but through his own inclination and vigilancy, he had much aſſiſted this State, by ſending auxiliary troups in moſt of Frontiers in Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, Flanders, Maeſtricht, and into our Army it ſelf, wherefore they deſired, that he would call them back again, or make himſelf maſter of thoſe Cities in which they lay offering their aſſiſtance thereunto; but that noble Earl was too honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſo much as once to liſten to ſuch an hellish plot, declining as much as might be all conference with them and departed to Bruſſels, shortly after augmenting inſtead of calling back his auxiliary Troups. The English perceiving they could gain nothing upon him, departed the 26. dito from Antwerp over Calis for Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, where they arrived the laſt dito.</p>
               <p>The 26. July, the King brake up from Box tel, with Monſieur &amp; other Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, with a conduct of 14000. men, paſſing through the Meyery over Beringen, St. Truyen, Hanuyt, Charleroy, Queſnoy, directly to St. Germein, where he arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved 1. Auguſt: the Prince of Condé following him shortly after with moſt of the Gentry and Voluntaries: in which return they of Maſtricht, (as formerly &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward got very great booty, as daily going forth for prey, and ſince the beginning of the war till now, have got an incredible ſpoil, of which the Spanish Auxiliaries had not the leaſt part, whoſe horſe were moſt in this ſervice. The Duke of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth went home over Flanders, his Regiment of 2400. being melted away to 1500. And thus to the admiration of every one, this Companies was before Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt broken up, Monſr. de Turenne alſo, Generaliſſimo of the Kings Leger in the Netherlands, left the ſiege of the Bos, and marched higher up, ſome Troups at times appearing before Heuſden, and the Bos, to fetch in contribution, and burned ſome Villages about Breda.</p>
               <p>The Bishops of Colen &amp; Munſter had begun 28. July to play with their Canon upon Groeningen, &amp; to open their Loopgraves. They in the City were reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably provided, &amp; had prepared all things without for to hold out a ſiege. But that which was moſt of all, they had a gallant Governour, the Lord Rabenhaupt, and a notable Commander, the Duke of Holſtein Pleun, and other worthy Officers: The Governour took upon himſelf the whole management of the Militia and fortification, being very ſtrict in diſcipline of war, and very vigilant to look to all things: Hereby the Magiſtrate was fruſtrated of their opportunity, to play their parts, as they in other Cities did, and citizens and ſoldiers kept from mutiny. The Enemy made his approaches both out of the Munſters and Colish Quarters, shooting very hard continually, whereby they got to the Counterſcarp, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting without ceaſing fiery Bullets, Bombes, Granados, Stink-pots and Pitch-Garlands into the City. But they within both Citizens, Studens and Soldiers,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38464:44"/>
defended the City with unwearied pains: never appeared the leaſt diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt them; but contrary it increaſed, through the ſucceſſe of diverſe iſſuings forth upon them, and by the ſuccours of ſuch as came from other places, as many Regiments of Konings mark, ſome Frieſes, and the whole Regiment of Jorman of Amſterdam, beſide the ſupply of all neceſſary Proviſion and Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition. When they ſaw their Houſes through the force of the Bombes tumbling down, inſtead of being disheartened, they were the more encouraged, The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men themſelves ſtepping over the ruines of their habitations, to encourage their Husbands to the fight, they lightly eſteemed the loſſe of an Arm, Leg; Child or Friend, in reſpect of their purchaſed liberty, in which they continued with ſuch conſtant manfullneſſe and unwearied zeal, untill that the Enemy the 28. Auguſt was forced with shame to quit the ſiege. Oh! Praiſe-worthy Groeningers, how wickedly did other Cities betray themſelves; yet in truth, this of Groeningen could hardly be termed a ſiege, the City being onely cloſed at 2. or 3. Bulwarks, and the reſt free, being provided of all neceſſaries, never ſuſtaining a ſtorm, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furiouſly shot upon with Bullets and Granados, which did little hurt except to the houſes, although it is reported, they caſt in above 5000. Granados, many of them weighing 4. and 5. hundred pound a piece, which indeed did ruine that part of the City, but did little hurt to the people, there being not above 80. ſlain du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the whole ſiege, but very many of the Enemy, who beſides the wounded amounted toy number of 4536. under which were three Commanders, two Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants Colonels, 63. Captains, with many other Officers: many were taken priſoners, and about 5000. ran away, ſo that the army of 24000. was decreaſed to 14000. and an infinite number of Fire-works conſumed. The Enemy leaving the City, ſet their Tents and Leger-place on fire; but were fain to leave ſome Canon with much Ammunition and Leger inſtruments behind them, the which they of the City made good prize of, and ſlighted all the Enemies works.</p>
               <p>At Sea, ſince the battle of the 7. June, nothing conſiderable fell out, our Fleet ſtill keeping near Zealand, upon what ground is diverſly conjectured; The Enemies Fleet alſo ſeemed to have little ſtomack for another engagement, yet in the midſt of July they came before the Texel, in all appearance the deſign being to Land their men ſome where or other, but the Heavens by a ſtorm hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the ſame, which ſooner than they were willing drave one of their ships a sho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and ſent back many shattered home again, the reſt remaining croſſing about our Sea-ports, thinking in appearance yet to bring about their deſign: in the mean while, our Fleet having no conſiderable loſſe. But the Enemy having repaired their Ships for the moſt part, ſpread themſelves all about on Sea, for to watch our merchant men; but eſpecially our Ships returning from the Indies. And the 1. Auguſt ſome Seamen came hither in an Advice-Yaght from <hi>Chilon,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purſued by the English to our very Coaſt, and ſeeing no way or eſcape, they themſelves ſunk her, and ſo eſcaped in the Boat, however the English ſaved the ſaid Jaght, and brought it for England, but was of no great valew. The 6. dito, tidings came of 14. Eaſt-Indies Ships, happily arrived upon the Eems, who not knowing of the war, and having met with no English, ſaving two Frigats before the Eems, who made ſigns for aſſiſtance, but in vain; and therefore were fain to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38464:44"/>
ſuffer them all ſafely to get in, which being at the time of the beſieging of Groe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningen, the Fort Delf-zijl had the hap to be furnished with powder and shot out of Eaſt-India, the better to defend the ships. Suddenly many Smack-boats were ſent thither, to take out the fineſt Wares, and to bring them home over the <hi>Wadden,</hi> and our Ships of War went to the Eems, to fetch off theſe India Ships, all which by a ſpecial providence arrived at their ſeveral Ports without any hinderance, and the Fleet returned again to Zealand. And it is very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, that the English who had ſo long lurked for to prey upon our Eaſt-Indie ships, themſelves, of which the certain news came the 17. Auguſt, loſt a very rich Indie ship of their own, called the Faulcon, being taken by a Zealand Caper, and brought up at Bergen in Norway, eſteemed to be worth 1500000. gildens; After this nothing was done by both Fleets, the deſign of the Enemy, which was to Land on our Coaſts, being continually hindered by hard weather, in the mean while our Capers, which at the beginning of the War were not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, with many other that had Commiſſion from Zealand, went out to Sea, and yet daily do, which already have ſo much endammaged the French, and eſpecially the English, that their loſſe is rated at many millions.</p>
               <p>The condition of the remainder of our Country, we left under the ſad tumult of the Inhabitants, by which all things were like to come into a lamentable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and if I judge not a miſſe, in greater peril, than through the Armies of the French, every moment we being in danger to ſtrand upon the blind Rocks of the incenſed vulgar, of which the effects were ſo many and diverſe, that it would be too confuſed and tedious a work to rehearſe or read them; it will be ſufficient to relate the chiefeſt, by which may eaſily be judged of the reſt.</p>
               <p>Upon the general inſurrection of the Citizens againſt the Magiſtrates, it was in ſome Cities published, and Letters from his Highneſſe divulged dated the 9. July, wherein the Citizens were commanded to abſtain from ſuch manner of proceedings, and to let things remain as formerly they were, upon pain of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, and to be punished as diſturbers of the common peace, it being an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchemend on his Highneſſe authority as Stadholder, whoſe office it is to diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of the concerns of the Magiſtracy: wherefore if any in the Regency were guilty, they might be orderly charged, and being found guilty, should be according to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert punished. Hereupon the Citizens expected that his Highneſs would make a general reformation in the Government, but nothing came of it; and no wonder, for this Iron was too hot for him to lay hold on, the time not be ſuitable to begin a work of ſuch conſequence: Nevertheleſs, the Commons would ſo have it, and therefore they ſet upon the work again. Rotterdam and Dort diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed the moſt part of the Magiſtrates, and nominated others in their room: and in many other places, by threatning Petitions, the reſtitution of their Old Priviledges laid by, were required. Delf was taken in by the Peſants of Maes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and the Magiſtrates conſtrained to give them and the Citizens ſatisfaction. The like was done at der Gou, and at der Tholen the Peſants came to alter the Magiſtrates. At Zierickzee they brake the windows of the Town-houſe, but the Citizens shut out the Peſants that were entring, themſelves emptying the Town-houſe, shutting it up, and diſplacing all the Magiſtrates. At Middle-borough
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:38464:45"/>
the Citizens and common people had ſet upon the Magiſtrates till ſuch time the Pefants came, brake open the City gates, and lifting up the Doors from off the Bars, drew 7. of the Lords without the City, whom they would not let go till they had received ſatisfaction. Vliſſingen and ter Vere alſo turned all upſide down, and at ter Goes, the Citizens roſe up againſt ſome whom they termed Traytors: Leyden was deep in the reformation, depoſing all their Lords and shut up the Town-houſe. Haerlem did not much leſſe: In North-Holland the Women themſelves very buſy, to have things ordered to their mind. At Amſterdam alſo were meetings at their Doelens, ſome of whom, not ſatisfyed to have occaſioned great trouble in the Church, by following of Labadie (who now is ſaid to be married with the Lady of Sommelsdick) were ring-leaders alſo to do the like in the Policy: But the Magiſtrates according to their wonted wiſdom, deſirous to prevent the ſtorm approaching reſigned the whole Government, and every one his charge to the free diſpoſal and pleaſure of his Highneſs, who ſeeing the unavoidable neceſſity for the common peace, did according to the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the States General in date of 7. Auguſt, take in hand the altering of the Magiſtracy, diſpoſing thereof in ſome Cities as he thought beſt himſelf, in others he choſe out ſome of them that were upon nomination, in ſome he did it by Commiſſioners, which notwithſtanding gave not full content to all, but much disſatisfaction ſtill remained, which was not a little fomented by ſuch as imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſeves injuried by this alteration. But bleſſed be God, this drew no further diſaſter along with it, and that the Government was in ſome meaſure brought to a more ſetled poſture, by putting by ſuch as the commons ſuſpected. What concerns the plundrings, and perſonal aſſaultings, they were diverſe, whereby alſo the greateſt of the Land were in jeopardy, as Burgemaſter Graaf, the Ambaſſador de Groot, the Lord of Beverning; yea, the ancient Prince Maurice himſelf; yea, ſuch was the rage of the vulgar, as they threatned to plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the houſe of Admiral de Ruyter, which alſo was really done to many of the Magiſtrates houſes in diverſe Cities: but it shall ſuffice to note in its place one example thereof, happened at the Hague the 20. Auguſt.</p>
               <p>After the King of France his departure, the quitting of the ſiege before the Bos, the breaking up of Turrennes Leger, and the delivery of Groeningen, no great matter of concern paſſed between us and the Enemy, except ſome skirmishes, of which I will note the principal as they fell out.</p>
               <p>22. July, the Ambaſſador de Groot, who was the chief of the Commiſſioners ſent to the King of France, ſilently departed the Land with his Family, as percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that the change of time, would not permit the transactions with France to go forward, his Highneſſe not being altogether ſatisfyed with him therein; but diſavowing the ſame, declared, that he was ready to defend his Country to the utmoſt, and to hazard life and all for the ſame. De Groot wrote a Letter to the State in way of excuſe, that he was onely retired for to eſcape the machinations of his enemies, and the rage of the vulgar, by which for ſome while he had been in perill of being overwhelmed: That all his ſervices had been improved for the good of the Land; neither would yet undertake any thing to the prejudice of the State.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:38464:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>GRONINGEN</p>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:38464:46"/>26. dito, The Frieſes under Alua, were unawares aſſaulted by 13. Standards of the Bishop, between Dragten and Bergen, where the Frieſes being allured into an Ambush, would have fallen short, had they not been ſeconded, whereby thoſe of the Bishop were driven back with the loſs of 150. horſe, and onely 25. of our ſoldiers.</p>
               <p>31. dito, The Penſionaris <hi>de Wit,</hi> for the firſt time went to Church, after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his wounds, wherein he was the more haſty, for to have the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to be aſſiſtant to the dangerous condition of his brother the <hi>Ruart van Putten,</hi> who the 24. dito was brought from Dort to the Hague, and there kept priſoner. The 1. Auguſt, the Penſionar went and complimented his Highneſſe over his Illuſtrious Character and advance. The 4. dito, he appeared in the Seſſion of the States General: where he made an Oration of his great ſervices and care of the welfare of the State, but perceiving that in this conjuncture it could be no longer for the profit, but contrarywiſe to the diſadvantage of the Land, he therefore was come to lay down his office of Penſionarship, perhaps becauſe he foreſaw he was not like long to hold, or at leaſt to execute the ſame, and withal deſired that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the reſolution before taken, he might have his ſeat in the High Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell; but foraſmuch as there fell diſpute about the Ranck, and afterward Zealand was oppoſite to the Seſſion it ſelf, and as is reported the Chair of State was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied in the Church, he never after appeared in the Councel.</p>
               <p>Upon notice given in England of his Highneſſe advance to the Stadtholder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, came a reſcription dated 28. July, which his Highneſſe communicated to the State.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Letter of his Majeſty the King of Great Brittain, To his Highneſs the Prince of Orange.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>From Whitehall</hi> 
                           <date> the <hi>28. July 1672.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <salute>Coſin,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>MOnſieur van Reede having made report of the ſad condition to which you are brought, it went very near me, but which moſt troubled me was that you ſeem to have an appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, as if I had leſſe care and affection to you than formerly: I pray you, that you be pleaſed to aſſure your ſelf, that they are groundleſs apprehenſions, &amp; without cauſe, but on the contrary that I have the ſame tender reſpects and affection your perſon that ever I had, both in regard of your own worth, as in reſpect of that blood of which we both partake: Neither have I ever for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got any of the leaſt good ſervices which your Father in his life time hath shewed to me, the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations whereof shall alwayes remain engraven in the bottom of my heart. Be pleaſed, I pray, to believe, though the preſent State of things, have not permitted me to correſpond with you, and to communicate my deſigns and Treaties, which in all tranſactions I have undertaken with the moſt Chriſtian King, I have alwayes endeavoured to advance your Intereſt ſo far as the nature of the Treaty could any way permit. The inſolencies and continual Machinations againſt me, by thoſe that for ſome time ſince have had ſo great direction in the Government of the United Netherlands, have neceſſitated me to joyn with the moſt Chriſtian King, (who alſo hath the ſame Subject of complaint againſt them) to the end onely to caſt down that inſupportable great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Louveſteinish faction, and to aſſure our ſelves from the like future inſults and mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age: The truſt that I have to the Friendship of the moſt Chriſtian King, the affection he bears to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38464:47"/>
your Perſon, and his averſion to them which have manifeſted themſelves to be my Enemies as well as yours, do promiſe unto me a good iſſue out of all theſe turmoiles as to your ſelf, and in caſe the Inhabitants of thoſe Provinces, had in time conſidered their miſtake, and conferred upon you the authority and dignities, wherewith your Illuſtrious Predeceſſors have ſo worthily been poſſeſſed of, then without doubt, the ſaid moſt Chriſtian King and We should have continued in a perfect and aſſured friendship with the foreſaid Provinces. Notwithſtanding I am very much ſatisfied with what the Commons of thoſe Provinces now lately have done, chooſing you for their Stadtholder. And when I shall ſee, that affairs are brought to ſuch a ſtay, that it shall be no longer in the power of the ſaid violent faction, or another as malitious, to diſsolve or make fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, what is done, and that I shall be able to free my Subjects from the oppreſſion and injuries they have ſo long ſuſtained; I will endeavour to protect you and your friends, and improve all my intereſt with my Brother in law, the moſt Chriſtian King, for to yeeld to ſuch an iſſue to theſe embroiled affairs, that the whole World may perceive the particular care I bear to your Perſon, and what for your ſake I will do for the intereſt of the foreſaid Provinces. To be short, I would aſſure you, and you may certainly believe, that I have alwayes all manner of good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination and intention for your well being, as ſuch as you could deſire, and which alwayes may witneſſe that I am, and shall be,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Couſin</salute>
                        <signed>Your well-affectionate Uncle, and was under writ <hi>CHARLES REX.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Letter was diverſly interpreted, which I leave to every one to judge of as ſeemeth him good, but look upon it as meerly complimental, and expreſſing the Kings bitterneſſe againſt this State, under the name of the Governors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and I pityed thoſe who judged to ſee in it any affection of the King towards his Highneſſe, and for his ſake to this Country, or did hope by this change the eaſier to obtain an accommodation with England.</p>
               <p>1. Auguſt, Towards evening went out of Utrecht about 3000. men, moſt Horſe, having ſome pieces by them, with which the day after they came before Kroonenburg, where Captain Witze commanded with about 200. men, it was a ſtrong Fort, but not provided with Ammunition, of which the French with ſome loſſe made themſelves maſters, carrying away our Soldiers priſoners to Utrecht, which alſo they did to the Fort Loenerſloot, in which lay onely a few men, both which Forts a while after they left; by powder demolishing Kroo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenburg, and having plundered all Loenen and what was thereabout, retired with the ſpoil to Utrecht.</p>
               <p>8. dito, In the Quarters of his Highneſſe, Captain de Hing Yoſſa, who had laid in Weſel, was ſentenced by the High Councel of War to be beheaded, for co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardize, mutiny, and treachery. Colonel Mombas, who had betrayed the Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, was the ſame day his brother in law, de Groot, departed the Land, ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be deprived of all dignities and Offices, to be detained 15. years priſoner; but in the ſentence nothing was pronounced againſt his Perſon, but not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he eſcaped, and went over to the Enemy, upon which 3000. gildens was ſet upon him by proclamation. The 28. Auguſt, Colonel d'Oſſery for his unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs at Rijnberck, was beheaded in the Princes Leger, And the 23. Septemb.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38464:47"/>
the Commander van Zanten and Major Copes, for their unfaithfull carriage in the delivery of Weſel, were diſgraded and their Swords broken at their feet, and the firſt of theſe, in the preſence of the other, had the Sword ſtroke over his head, his Goods confiſcated, himſelf banished for 12. years out of the Land: another Colonel of Weſel alſo was diſgraded and ſent away; other Officers of Rijnberck, Weſel, and other places, for their cowardize were detained priſoners, ſome at Maſtricht, others at Gorcum and Bodegrave.</p>
               <p>10. dito, Some Horſe out of the Quarters of his Highneſſe; advanced to the very gates of Utrecht, rushing into the Enemies retrenchment, killing many and bringing away 16. priſoners, with the loſſe of two men onely. About this time, our Militia was muſtered by the Lord Beverning here, and by others in other places, and were found to be 783. Companies, 200. whereof had their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers diſcharged, to be (as they ſpeak) reformed, and their Companies added to other; which alſo shortly after was effected by his Highneſſe, and theſe reformed Officers had a certain maintenance allotted them, with promiſe to be again ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced according to merit, with the firſt opportunity.</p>
               <p>12. dito, His Highneſſe came to Amſterdam, all the 60. Companies with two Companies of Horſe were in Arms, and the 13. dito his Highneſſe took Seſſion in the City Councel, and of the Admiralty, having before taken a view of the City fortifications, and at noon was treated in the Town-houſe, then he depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Muyen, for to ſee the fortifications there, &amp; ſo to Weeſp, Hinderdam and Abkow, from whence he again returned the 14. dito, and the day following de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted in pomp to Bodegrave.</p>
               <p>18. dito, A Troup of French Horſe of 17. Standards, intended to have ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized Gorcum, but the Field Marshal Wurts having notice thereof, ſent ſome Foot with 3. Pieces againſt them, forcing them after the loſſe of 60. Horſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to Vianen and Utrecht, 4. onely of our men being ſlain.</p>
               <p>The 20. dito, was fatal to two of the chief Perſons of the Land, <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his brother <hi>Iohan de Wit,</hi> the firſt being old Burgomaſter of Dort, and Ruard of the Land of <hi>Putten,</hi> being late the onely Plenipotentiary on the Fleet, The other Great Counceller, and Penſionaris of Holland and Weſt-Frieſland: It was the 24. July when the Ruart was by the Fiſcale of the Court, brought pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner from Dort to the Hague, being lodged in Caſteleiny, it being not known for what, ſave onely that a Barber of Bodegrave accuſed him, that by money he ſought to entice him, having alſo given a part of the promiſed ſum, to kill his Highneſſe; whereupon being examined by the Court, and diverſe times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted with the Accuſer, he was the 6. of Auguſt brought from the Caſteleinye into the Fore-poort of the Court, his Accuſer alſo being a while after there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, and after diverſe confrontings, The Ruart was put to the torture, which he endured as is ſaid, two times, And the 20. dito in the morning, the Accuſer was ſet at liberty, the following Sentence being pronounced againſt the Ruart, priſoner in the Court Gate.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:38464:48"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="sentence">
                           <head>The SENTENCE of the Court of Holland and Weſt-Frieſland, againſt Mr. CORNELIUS de WIT, Old Burge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter of the City <hi>Dort,</hi> pronounced the 20. Auguſt 1672.</head>
                           <p>THe Court of Holland having ſeen and examined the Papers, delivered up by the Procureur General of the ſaid Court, to the Charge of <hi>Mr. Cornelius de Wit,</hi> Old Burgemaſter of Dort, and <hi>Ruard</hi> of the Land of <hi>Putten,</hi> at preſent Priſoner in the Fore-gate of the ſaid Court, together with his Examinations and Confrontations, as what by the ſaid Priſoner hath been delivered up, and having duely conſidered what was in the caſe to be taken notice of, or might any wayes be ſerviceable in it; Do declare the Priſoner to be fallen from all his Dignities and Offices by him hitherto poſſeſſed of; and further doth banish him the Country of Holland and Weſt-Frieſland, ſo as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to return again upon pain of greater punishment, and that he depart the Country with the very firſt; condemning him in the Charges and Miſes of the Law, at the taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and moderation of the ſaid Court. Acted by the Lords <hi>Adriaen Pauw</hi> Preſident, Lord of Bennebroeck, <hi>Aelbrecht Nierop, William Goes,</hi> Lord of Boeckhorſtenburg, <hi>Fredrick van Lier,</hi> Lord van Soetermeer, <hi>Cornelius Baen,</hi> and <hi>Matheus Gool,</hi> Councellors of Holland and Weſt-Frieſlend, and pronounced upon the Fore gate of the Court, the <hi>20.</hi> Auguſt, <hi>1672.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Witneſſe hereof <hi>A. Dr. POTS.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>The Citizens having a few dayes before heard a rumour that the <hi>Ruard</hi> was eſcaped, would not be quiet, before he had shown himſelf before the grates of the windows, and from that time kept the priſon gate with watch. Seeing the Barber come off free, and hearing that the <hi>Ruard</hi> onely was banished, began again tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuouſly to riſe up, and ſet on by the inſtigation of the Barber, all the 6. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies roſe up in Arms. In the mean while, <hi>John de Wit</hi> came with his Father in a Coach, for to fetch away his brother, according to the <hi>Ruards</hi> deſire, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe of tumult riding away with the Coach: when now both the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers came from above, they were forced by the Citizens that kept the watch to go up again, till that two whole Companies came to the Gate, who with their Pikes and Muſquets drave away the Horſe that were coming thither; In the mean while, the mutiny of the Citizens encreaſed, crying now we have both the Traytors within, they shall not eſcape us; and two of the Citizens Officers, with ſome Gentlemen of the Companies and Commons went up to bring them down, where they found the <hi>Ruard</hi> in his Gown upon his bed, and <hi>John</hi> ſitting before him, who with ſoft words and in way of excuſing did pacifie theſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and prevailed with them to ſit down at Table to eat: by which ſtay and the encreaſe of the vulgar, the tumult roſe to an extream height, and ſo shot they fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly at the priſon Gate, and at length with iron Inſtruments brake it in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as alſo ſome inner-doores: upon which the doore of the priſon chamber was opened, <hi>John de Wit</hi> asking, well good people, to what end is all this force? but ſeeing it was their intent to cauſe them to come down, he took his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38464:48"/>
brother by the hand, and went with much thruſting and kicking down the ſtairs: coming below, <hi>John</hi> thought to have gone behind the armed men, and not thorow the ranks; but was by the vulgar preſently ſeiſed on, and by a citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen ſtroke on the head with the thick end of his musquet, ſo that he fell down, but ſoon roſe up again; but at the ſecond blow he ſunk down to the ground, and then a citizen ſetting his foot upon his neck, shot him with a pocket piſtol thorow the head: The <hi>Ruard</hi> was ſerved in the ſame kind, being fallen upon, beaten, shot, and thruſt thorow, and his dead Corps troden upon, and the Gown of the <hi>Ruard,</hi> and Cloak of <hi>John</hi> torn into ſmall pieces with their cloths, and ſo thrown about.</p>
               <p>It remained not thus onely, but their dead bodies were dragged to the place of execution, and hanged by their feet ſtark naked upon the aſſents of the Gibbet, in the ſight of all the World; whereupon the vulgars fury not yet ſatisfyed, they toward the evening firſt cut off the two foremoſt fingers of <hi>John de Wit,</hi> wherewith he had ſubſcribed the perpetual Edict, and afterward cut of the Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Toes, Noſe, Ears, and privy Members of both of them, and prying into the innermoſt parts, plucked out their Bowels, winding them about their arms, tore their Hearts out of their boſoms, ſcrewed open their Bodies with wooden pricks, offering to ſale in all parts of the City; yea, in other Towns inlandish and outlandish the torn pieces of their Garments, and Members of their bodies; A Toe was ſold for 10. the joynt of a Finger for 12. a Finger for 15. and an Ear for 25. ſtuyvers, and ſo <hi>pro rato,</hi> accordingly, ſome of them they dryed, embal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and carried about to be ſeen for money, and they that went to the higheſt pitch of inhumanity, did <hi>(horreſco referens)</hi> roſt their Flesh and ate it. Who would believe that ever our Netherlands should have brought forth <hi>Anthropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phagi?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The night drawing her Curtains before this tragical Theatre, the Actors and Spectators departed; whereupon came a Coach with five Laquies, which took away what was left of the Bodies, bringing the ſame into the Houſe of <hi>Iohn de Wit</hi>; burying the ſame ſilently the next night in the New Church, in the Grave where <hi>Iohn de Wits</hi> Wife laid: Some there were that ſpake of taking them up out of the Graves again, to burn them to ashes, and fling them into the air; fearing perhaps, leaſt by another change of time, their bones should rear them up, a Grave of honour as Martyrs of the State, as was formerly foretold, should be done to <hi>Barnevelt.</hi> However, they ſatisfyed themſelves in putting their hands to the laſt work of breaking to fitters their Arms, which were made to be hung up in the Church, for they would root out their memory, if they could, as well as their Lives from the Earth.</p>
               <p>Their kindred complying with the intemperance of theſe times, did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in mourning apparel: Strangers ſpake of the tranſaction, as their fancies led them, ſome judged it an act of Chivalry and reſtauration of our oppreſſed li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; Others did not commend, yet would not blame it, looking upon it as a ſpecial judgement upon them; yet many condemn the whole action, fearing the deſtruction of the whole Land would follow hereupon; but they who would ſeem
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:38464:49"/>
the moſt impartial, judged that in this conjuncture of time, it was a good ſervice to the Land, that theſe men were removed, though they were the greateſt Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligents and Politicians of the World; yet the action it ſelf they lookt upon as barbarous and abominable, and which hath ſtained our Nation with the black mark of fury, which shall never be wiped of, and the more becauſe no certain evidence, or confeſſion of the one, nor accuſation of the other hath been made known. This is remarkable, that at the very ſame time the Citizens were here buſie to take away the life of <hi>John de Wit,</hi> who had reſigned his Penſionaryship, even the States of Holland, during theſe tumults were employed in the choice of another Penſionaris, unto which the Lord Griffier Fagel was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</p>
               <p>1. September, The Field Marshal Wurts went with ſome Troups out of Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, to the Houſe Pouroyen, which the French had fortified, and garriſoned, which he ſoon maſtered, taking ſome priſoners, the reſt retiring to Bommel: and while ours were buſie in this work, they of the Bos went before Crevecoeur, to impede that no aſſiſtance from thence might be ſent to Pouroyen, which being ſometime beſet with our men, was ſoon after demolished by Gun-powder.</p>
               <p>2. dito, Some Frieſes with help of them that croſſe upon the Souther-Sea, fell upon Block-zijl, and gayned the Sconſe by them erected, upon which the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants fell upon the Munſters, and cut the throat of the Commander, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with by help of ours Soldiers did drive out the French, whereupon Vollenhoven was alſo left by the Enemy.</p>
               <p>About this time, alſo ſome Yaghts and Small-ships with Soldiers under the conduct of one Muller, went from Amſterdam with a deſign upon Swart-ſluce, before which after long hinderance by contrary wind, they came; but the plot not being well laid, did not proſper, the Munſters being ſeconded by their friends, whereupon ſome of ours returned to Amſterdam, leaving there the Yaght of Muller, which was fired: but moſt of ours made for Block-zijl, from whence the 11. dito, Captain Holbaarn with 240. men made a gallant aſſault up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Slijckenburg, or the Kuynder-Sconſe, ſoon putting 250. of the Epiſcopel to flight, taking 28. priſoners, a Coach with horſes, and other booty, few being ſlain or wounded on either ſide, Captain Holbaarn remained Commander there.</p>
               <p>7. dito, Toward evening 2000. Groeningers with 12. Field Pieces went forth out of Groeningen, under the chief Lieutenant of the Governor Rabenhaupt, to Winſchoten, which the Epiſcopal were a making ſtrong, by that Fortreſſe to ſtraiten the Bourtange, Delf-zijl, yea Groeningen it ſelf; Whereupon the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopal being 800. Dragoons went the 8. dito out of Winſchoten, and ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in poſture by four Eſquadrons in the Field till ours came, but were ſoon put to flight, and withal driven out of the Winſchoter Sconſe, looſing about 200. man, ſix pieces, many waggons, ſpades, and ſuch like Inſtruments, retiring unto the Old and New Sconſes; after which ours put a Garriſon in the Fort Te Wedde, which is the Pas to the Bourtange, whereby the Paſſes of the Old and New Sconſes are aſmuch as poſſible could be shut and blockt up.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:38464:49"/>16. dito, Some Troups from the quarter of the Earl of Horn, marched into Oudewater, putting forces into it, making ſoon after his quarters there, leaving the Poſt of Gouverwelle ſluce beſet with ſome Troups onely: Which alſo his Highneſs would have done at Woerden, if they had not been unwilling to ſpoil their Tile-houſes, ſo deſired they might be excuſed, whereupon his Highneſſe ſeeing he could not be ſecured, put no forces into the Town, but the French awakened through our ſtrengthening of Oudewater, the Duke of Luxenburgh, Stoupa, Mombas, and many other Officers, marched from Utrecht with about 4. or 5000. Horſe and Foot, 4. Peeces, and much bagage to Woerden, where ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving the Duke, by a Trumpetter deſired of the Lords paſſage for ſome Troups, which was granted: whereupon they all entred, and held their Poſt there, to the great aſtonishment of the Inhabitants: The 19. dito, many boats with bagage and proviſion, alſo carts with inſtruments and bullets, and two Canons, (for the other did ſtick in the way) were ſent in, and with all ſpeed the Peſants round about with the Citizens were forced to work at the fortification, for the ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of the City, and to leave all they had without the City, and demolish whatever ſtood in the way, ſo Luxenburg returned to Utrecht, leaving a Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of 2000. there.</p>
               <p>20. dito, Some French went from Crevecoeur to Heuſden, and on a ſudden rushed into a Redout and Horn-work, which they of the City perceiving, were alarmed, whereupon the French were forced again to retire out of thoſe Poſts, taking along with them ſome priſoners; but on the other hand, at the ſame time a French Troup of Horſe near the Village Capel, a little higher than Schoonho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven were ſoundly beaten, and many ſlain, without any great loſſe of our men.</p>
               <p>4. dito, The Sommer ſeaſon paſſing, our Fleet came in, ſome lighter Frigats keeping Sea near our Ports, the greater ships retiring to their ſeveral homes, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which alſo the greater English ships were laid up, one Eſquadron of the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ships onely keeping at Sea, The French Eſquadron alſo prepared to go home, but were kept at Sea by contrary winds till the midſt of November, before they got to Breſt: And it is paſt apprehenſion, how theſe two Fleets Enemies to each other could be ſo long, without any engaging.</p>
               <p>The War which till now hath been ſo ſore upon us, was driven on by the profeſſed enmity of 2. mighty Kings, one Elector, and the Bishop of Weſtpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, beſides many other who under hand did favour and aſſiſt them: where on the contrary, we onely a little ſupplied by the Spanish Netherlands, were forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of all our former Allies. With Brandenburg indeed a Treaty defenſive was made, but hitherto without any effect, untill that the Lords of Amerongen and Pelnits took their journey thither with vaſt ſums, but the ship in which they were, happily met a boat from Hamburg before the Weſet, who told them there lay three English ships before the Elve, which waited for the coming of an Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ship with money, and that, if they would but look up they might ſee them; wherefore it ſeemed moſt ſafe to theſe Lords, to ſail with the money to Bremen, where they well arrived; from that time forward, there was a gathering of ſome Soldiers, of which continually was much ſpoken and long expectation; At the ſame time alſo the Emperor raiſed forces at Egra, according to a league defenſive
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:38464:50"/>
between him and Brandenburg, for the ſecurity of the Empire againſt France, in which league Spain and Denmarck alſo were included, which to us ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to promiſe ſome good, and the rather becauſe it was certainly report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Brandenburgers traine came down, and the Elector himſelf 26. Auguſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at Halberſtadt, where alſo the Earl Montecuculi, General of the Imperial Troups came the 10. September. It was expected that both theſe Armies would have come further to the Rhijn ſide, and preſſe into Wephalia: were upon, alſo Turenne gathered his Forces and encamped between Weſel and Doesburg, for to have a waking eye upon them: but the Auxiliary Troups having laid ſome while about Halberſtadt, changed their courſe, returning back to Franckfurt, The Elector leaving ſome Forces upon the borders of Weſtphalia, and the Auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaries ſate down at Fridburg and Butspach; whereupon Turenne alſo marched up higher with his Army, alongſt the Rhijn, and pitched over againſt Ceulen.</p>
               <p>And notwithſtanding, we here were altogether ignorant of the intent the Auxiliaries had in this march, yet it put ſome courage into us; for hereby Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennes Army was kept off from us, and in the interim our Armies encreaſed mightily with inlandish and outlandish Forces, as diverſe Regiments of Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nincksmark, The General Polens, of the Duke of Holſtein Pleun, of the Earl of Witgenſtein, and the like, which came out of other Countries, the method alſo of the Militia was better ordered; the Leger Poſts in better defence, and the commotions at home ſedated, all which gave more ſatisfaction to the Citizens; but on the contrary, it encreaſed the miſery of the conquered places, and daily augmented their oppreſſion: On the plains all was ruinated by fire and ſword, in the Cities exceſſive burdens and contributions raiſed, and Soldiers inquartered in the Citizens houſes, and themſelves diſarmed; and upon high threats of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment required to bring all their Arms up to the Town-houſe to be lockt up: Diverſe of their Churches, contrary to agreement, taken from them, and thorowout all the Conqueſt the following Proclamation of the King was pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished Whereupon on the other hand by way of retorſion, a like Proclamation was published by the States.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="declaration">
                           <head>A Declaration of the French King, againſt the Inhabitants of Gelderland, Over-Yſſel, and the Sticht Utrecht.</head>
                           <p>FRom the King: His Majeſty being well informed, that a great number of the Inhabitants of the new conquered Lands by his Arms in Holland, have aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned and forſaken their Lands, Houſes, and Inheritances, retiring themſelves elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; His Majeſties pleaſure being to force them to return, doth ordain and command expreſly, that the owners of the ſaid Houſes thus abandoned, do come and dwell there again, and that before the end of this month now running on, without any longer delay, upon pain, the time being paſt of confiſcation of all their incomſtes, and to be obliged every day to pay <hi>50.</hi> gilders for the maintenance of the Troups of his Majeſty, and in caſe of no payment, their Houſes to be raſed down to the ground, their plantations ruinated.</p>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>portrait of Raymundus Graef</figDesc>
                              <head>RAYMUNDUS GRAEF van MONTE CUCCOLI Generalisſimus van t. Keiserlück Leger:</head>
                           </figure>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                              <p>NAARDEN</p>
                           </figure>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                              <p>UYTERMEER SLUYS</p>
                           </figure>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                              <p>WEESP</p>
                           </figure>
                           <p>
                              <pb n="49" facs="tcp:38464:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>His Majeſty commands and ordains to his Lieutenants General, Commanders of his Troups in the conquered Countries, as alſo to the Lord <hi>Robert</hi> Intendant of the Juſtice Polity and Finances, in his regard to look unto the execution of theſe preſents, the which his Majeſty will have published, and in all places affixed, where it's require, that none may pretend ignorance hereof. Given at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> the <hi>9.</hi> Septemb. <hi>1672.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Was ſubſcribed <hi>LOUIS. Yet lower LE TELLIER.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>In England the time of the Parliaments coming together approached, but it pleaſed the King to prorogue them untill February next coming, of which there were diverſe thoughts, but moſt judged it a ſign of ſmall inclination to peace, which ſeemed the more credible, becauſe of the news, that France and England bad prolonged the Alliance for 6. moneths.</p>
               <p>The 28. dito, Ours made an attempt upon Naarden, to which end many ships went with Soldiers from der Gow to the Southern Sea, and from Amſterdam and other Poſts with boats to Weeſp, for to fall upon Naarden altogether at one time early in the morning, both by Water and by Land; the Soldiers at Land, with whom his Highneſſe was in perſon being ready at the ſet time, and were advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced near unto the City, they within not yet knowing of it, but by reaſon of an extraordinary calm, the Soldiers in the ships, nor the Float-boats with the Canon could come up, ſo the attempt came to nothing, for his Highneſſe not willing to hazard his forces, which might have been fallen upon from behind out of Amers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord and Utrecht, drew off the Militia to their Poſts, onely leaving ſome Poſted in Grave-land and Ankeveen.</p>
               <p>Octob. 7. Some French (who upon the attempt of Naarden were come from Utrecht) fell upon ours, who were Poſted in Graven-land, putting to flight, and taking ſome of them priſoners; whereupon the French advanced before the Sluce of Ankeveen, where Prince Maurice had planted ſome Palliſados, and caſt up of a ſudden a Breſt-work, upon which the French ſell on with great fury, but were repulſed with the loſſe of fifty men, and on our ſide onely one Captain.</p>
               <p>10. dito, An attempt upon Woerden was made, the Lord of Zuyleſtein out of the Princes Quarter, and the Earl of Horn out of Ouwater, coming in the night before it, but paſſed by to their appointed poſts; Zuyleſtein with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of Solms, and ſome other Companies Groven-bridge, betwixt Ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recht and Woerden, to hinder ſuccours from Utrecht, poſting there with a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery toward Utrecht: The Earl of Horn having by him ſome Companies of Mariners lay Poſted upon Polanen and the Saw-mills, to shoot upon the City from thence. The 11. dito, with the breaking of the day, the Watch-man on the Tower ſpyed, that there were Forces come before the City, and ſounding twice the Bells, all was alarmed in the City, and the ſound of Muſquets heard, anſwered one another: Whereupon the Watch made a fire upon the South-eaſt Corner of the Walk, for a ſign to them of Utrecht, that they were in ſtreſſe for
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38464:53"/>
ſuccours, and the wind blowing very hard, the Tower, Church, and 15. or 16. Houſes were conſumed to ashes, the fire during till the afternoon. In the mean while, his Highneſſe made his approaches to the City from the ſide of Bode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave, to make an attempt upon it; but they within ſent forth ſome to ſet on fire the Tile-houſes, it being about the evening which in meaſure ſucceeded, but they were ſoon driven in again by ours: At which time the Duke of Luxenburg with 6. a 7000. men, fell upon the quarter of Zuyleſtein, but was manfully reſiſted: The 12. dito, early in the morning, the Princes men ſcaled the walls by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Fire-balls and Granados, upon which they within iſſued out, but fell short, and ſoon returned back to the City, leaving behind many dead, among which were 18. Officers, being followed by our men to the very gates, which the French had out of a ſudden fear left a good while open, and without guard, so as it might by our men have eaſily been taken, had they gone forward.</p>
               <p>While this was a doing, and all things prepared to force the City, for which the Prince himſelf in perſon advanced to the very Gate, the Duke of Luxenburgh (who the night before was beaten off from the quarter of Zuyleſtein) through the help of ſome Peſants was led along the Houdijck to Camerijck, and from thence came by the Cruipin (though the waters were knee-deep and higher) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Woerden and the quarter of Zuyleſtein, and on a ſudden fell upon them from behind, where it was naked and the Canon turned: and however they fought manfully, yet that quarter not able to ſtand out againſt the whole power of the French, would have been ruined, in caſe the Earl of Horn, had not come to their aſſiſtance, who fell upon the French with ſuch courage, that many were ſlain, fighting with the rapier in their hand, and the Mariners with their knives. By which defence our men had opportunity to retire in order, onely the Canon of Zuyleſtein, with his Ammunition was taken; but the Earl of Horn brought of his men, and ſummoned the City before he departed: And his Highneſſe hearing the tidings hereof, gave order to retire with the whole train, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Leger poſts, the city by theſe ſuccours being too much fortifyed, for to attempt further upon it. In this encounter indeed the deſign upon the City did not proſper, yet there was no diſadvantage in the battle; there being loſt on our ſide not above 500. men in all, both priſoners and ſlain, among was the Lord Zuyleſtein, and Lieutenant Colonel Schimmel-penning, on the other hand the French loſt above two thouſand, among whom were ſome of great qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity with many high and inferior Officers, ſo that France it ſelf did not greatly boaſt of this encounter.</p>
               <p>At the ſame time it was appointed, that the Garriſon of Schoonhoven should make a diverſion, under the Marquis de Lovigni, and alarm Vreeſwijck, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called de Vaert, over againſt Vianen, which was alſo done, with ſuch ſucceſs that our men approaching longſt the Dike, with the loſſe of 7. or 8. under which were two Captains, entered the ſame, but inſtead to advance further and fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the French, who not above an hundred meanly retrenched lay below the Sluce, every one fell a plundering, and with their booty retired, ſetting ſome houſes on fire; whereupon the French came afterward and burnt down the Church it ſelf with ſome other houſes. At the ſame time alſo it was ordered to make a falſe alarm about Naarden, but had no effect.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>WOERDEN</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>OUDE WATER</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:38464:54"/>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:38464:54"/>17. dito, 36. Out of Aardenburg aſſaulted the Fort Knocke, laying on the Vaart, upon the Steen-ſtraet, where the French had a Cuſtom-houſe, which they took in, killing many of the French, and taking 25. priſoners, among whom was the Cuſtom-maſter and the Controller, brought with them the Kings Arms, with good booty, ſetting the Forton fire, but was afterward again reared by the French.</p>
               <p>The 17. dito, the great Councel of War was held at der Gow, where were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his Highneſſe, and the Generals of the Leger, but their Conſultations were kept very cloſe: but ſoon after, a great number of Inland-ships to the number of 800 or 1000. were arreſted, with which the 26. dito and following dayes from Rotterdam and der Gow were shipped the moſt part of the States Horſe, and ſome Regiments of Foot, to the Brabants Coaſts, being followed by ſome of the greateſt Commanders and his Highneſſe himſelf, who brought them into po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture about Breda, and marched into the Country of Luyck, with what deſign is kept very ſecret.</p>
               <p>26. dito, The Munſters with 1400. came along the Long Acker or New-ſconſe, and fell upon ours for to raiſe the ſiege of the Belling wolder or Old-ſconſe, but were ſo welcomed, that they were forced ſoon to retire to the New-ſconſe, 200. and more being ſlain and ſtript, whereupon thoſe of the Old-ſconſe the 27. dito began to parly, and departed thence with burning match, to the number of 400. of which ſcarcely an 100. came into Coeverden, and our men did with all ſpeed labour to block up the New-ſconſe, as cloſe as poſſibly might be; but foraſmuch as it cannot be well approached to, and they within vvell provided, it may in all appearance hold out long.</p>
               <p>The Emperial and Brandenburger Forces kept along while about Franckfurt, where were held diverſe Conferences with the Princes thereabout, touching the marching of theſe people through their Territories, the Elector of Ments, being reſolved to hinder their coming over the Rhijne; and therefore took away the Bridge before the City, whereupon the Confederates in the beginning of November made a Ship-bridge over the Main near Fleersheim, where fell out skirmishes about Uſingen, where ſome of the Emperialiſts guarding a Pas over the Lhaan, were ſet upon by ſome Companies of Turenne, who himſelf with his Army marched from Colen up higher, and was already advanced near Coblents and the Weſter-wald: This encounter fell out to the advantage of the Confederates, they keeping the Pas, though they were fewer in number, and the 7. and 8. dito, they paſſed over the Bridge they had made; the Emperial Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Montecuculi being to depart to Weenen, and the Duke de Bourneville to come in his place to command the Emperial Troups: And at this time the Prince of Condé was come to Mets, to gather an Army about the Moeſel, to withſtand the Confederates, to which end all was brought together in France, what poſſible could be, to ſend to Condé: The 24. dito, the Duke of Anjou, who was born, while the King was in the Field died. The French fearing that the Emperialiſts would march longſt the Bergſtraat through the Palts, and paſſe the Rhijn at Straatsburg over the Bridge, to come into the Elſes, thereupon the Commander in Briſack shipping 700. men, came the 16. November in the night and burnt the Bridge at Straatsburg, ruining 8. arches thereof, to the great aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38464:55"/>
of the Straatsburgers: but the Emperialiſts not ſeeking that way, made a Bridge over the Rhijn a little higher than Maints, and in part marched over the ſame; Whereupon alſo the Marshal Turenne laid a Bridge over the Rhijne, ſomwhat below Coblens by Andernach, and departed with ſuch ſpeed out the Bergsland and Weſterwald, that the ſick and overweary were left behind above a 1000. in number, all which by the Peſants there about were put to the Sword.</p>
               <p>November 4. 400. French came into the Vïllage Waverveen, where the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants at firſt made ſome reſiſtance, but ſoon retired; an Outlayer having in it 28. men, and ſome iron pieces, defended it ſelf couragiouſly, but ran a ground, and ſo was maſtered, whereupon the French plundered the Town, much abuſing the Peſants, and before they departed, ſet the Town on fire. The 7. dito, they burnt down the remaining Tile-houſes about Woerden, as alſo the 8. dito the Villages Newveen and Over-meer: and the 9. a Fort by Newerbrugge, and wholy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by fire that fair Town of Jaarsvelt, and the 16. dito, ſet on fire Abkow, nothing being exſpected, but this Winter they will ruinate all the open Country where ever they can come.</p>
               <p>14. dito, A party of 400. out of Ouwater, ſurprized 14. ships with Hay by Monfoort, with Oats, Straw and Corn, intending for Utrecht, ſome they brought with them, the reſt they burnt. And the day following, the Marquis De Tours Commander of the Goverwelle-ſluce with a gallant party, ſet upon many Boats with proviſion, going for Utrecht and Woerden, taking 30. of them, and ſunk 8. before Woerden, whereupon ſoon after the French deſerted the Cities Yſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein and Monfoort, blowing up the Tower of the Fort of Monfoort.</p>
               <p>16. dito, The Munſters forſook the Yler-ſconſe, becauſe, as it ſeemed, 2500. Horſe of the Prince of Courland, taken into ſervice of this State, were arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at Lier in Eaſt-Frieſland, for to come here into our Country through Groe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningen. About an hundred of our men laying before the Old-ſconſe, were commanded to take poſſeſſion of the Yler-ſconſe; whereupon a day two or three after 3000. Munſters fell on again, driving our men out, and taking ſome priſoners, as alſo routed 200. of the Courlanders, who were gone a graſing too far in Weſtphaly, yet many of theſe afterward made shift to return to their main body: the Munſters loſt not many leſſe in this rencountre, and quitting the Yler-ſconſe, it was well nigh wholy ruinated.</p>
               <p>2. dito, 50. men out of Block-zijl made a party, and hard by Haſſelt encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred 36. of Colen with a Lieutenant whom with 24. they took priſoners, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the reſt. The 28. dito, The French came to the Poſt of Ankeveen, from which they were forced to retire with the loſſe of 8. men, and 4. or 5. priſoners; yet in their retiring burnt ſome houſes behind the Town. The 30. dito, they came again to Abkow, thinking to burn down the remaining of it, but our men falling out of the Fort, hindred the ſame, and took 30. of them priſoners; and ſome other of ours in a boat, went to Breukelen, and fetcht 19. French from thence, and brought them priſoners to Abkow.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>SWART SLUYS</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>fortifications</figDesc>
                  <p>HASSELT</p>
               </figure>
               <p>29. dito, 500. men from Block-zijl and the Kuynder, came before Swartſluce with 30. Capers, and 3. very great Flat-boats, which were fenced and provided with great Guns, or half Cartows, having about a 1000. men in them for to Land, and ſo altogether to fall upon the Sluce: 200. of our Land-ſoldiers fell on ſo ſtoutly at the appointed time, that they had even got the maſtery of the Fort, but the Ships and Boats advanced not, but kept off, shooting at a diſtance, doing little or no hurt to the Enemy; our Men on Land making ſign with their Hats for them to ſail forward, but in vain, though they had both wind and ſtream for their advantage; whereupon a party of Horſe from Haſſelt and Meppel came rushing on, falling upon the back of our men, and took in the Fort again, about an 100. of ours, either ſlain, drowned, or wounded, and near 200. taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which was imputed to the treachery or cowardize of ſome, for had they that fell on, as was meet been ſeconded, they had not only got Swart-ſluce, but Haſſelt alſo, which was the intent of the enterprize; but this was the ſecond time brought to nothing, to our shame and loſſe.</p>
               <p>The ſeaſon of the year, the badneſſe of the wayes, and ill ſucceſs of our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, did ſufficiently shew, that this Winter time very little good was within the Country to be exſpected: as alſo it could not help much to the redreſſing of our decaying State, in caſe it could have been attainable for us this Winter to gain Naarden, Woerden, yea, Utrecht it ſelf; therefore it was a moſt prudent and praiſe-worthy reſolution, and an undertaking of a more glorious and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er deſign of his Highneſs, leaving the Land in a good poſture of defence, to go forth and meet the Enemy upon the borders, not shunning to face them in the Field; hereby peradventure being like to put a short iſſue to a long War. And however it might fall out with the undertaking, the ſucceſſe whereof depends on the bleſſing of the Lord; nevertheleſs, the Impartial will in equity free him from that imputation, wherewith the enviers of his Greatneſs and proſperity have beſpattered him, and be conſtrained to confeſs, that the liberty of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is more precious than his Life, &amp; that his Princely youth doth not come short of any of the nobleſt undertakings of his Illuſtrious Predeceſſours.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:38464:57"/>This State not being ſatisfyed with the pretended neutrality of the Country of Luyck, where the French had put Forces in the Cities of Maſeyck, Tongeren, and Valckenburg, and fortifying the whole Country (though againſt the will of the States of Luyck) and kept under their devotion; Therefore on our ſide alſo the ſaid Country was ſet undër contribution, and with force furthered, upon which there followed enmity between Luyck and Maſtricht, all commun<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being cut off: In the mean while, they of Luyck by Deputies in the Hague, and the interceſſion of the Spanish Ambaſſador, deſired a ceſſation of further proceedings in way of enmity, and for Treaty of friendship, upon which the Earl of Slodorp went for Luyck, and the former correſpondence was re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished; eſpecially, when his Highneſſe was come thither to whom they ſent Preſents, and proffered all neceſſaries and aſſiſtance of men for the ſervice of the State, ſo that all endeavour was made to ſecure that Princedom to this State, and his Highneſſe with all his power laboured to engage Duras, who commanded the French Troups in Luyckland, following him even to Colen; but he with great dayes journies leaving the Maas, retired to the Moeſel, though he were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruted with ſome of the Forces of the Earl De Lorge. In the mean while, our Forces ſeized upon Valkenburg, and demolished it, taking 200. priſoners in the ſame, and brought to Maſtricht, and blockt up Tongeren with the help of the Spaniards, who now did no longer ſecretly with ſome bands, but openly with all might and main, Horſe and Foot and Artillery oppoſe the French, and in their publick prayers begged for a bleſſing on their Arms againſt them: and, as is ſaid, by their Ambaſſador at Paris required the reſtitution of the Places taken from them in the laſt War, by the French.</p>
               <p>The Imperialiſts and Brandenburgers ſtill remained with their Forces betwixt the Main and the Rhijn, guarding their Bridges over both thoſe Rivers, and by ſome Horſe had ſecured to themſelves Keyſerlauter, being a Pas to Mets, whereabout the Prince of Condé yet lyeth, and on the other ſide of the Moeſel the Marshal de Turenne, to whom the Earl Duras hath adjoyned himſelf: What will be iſſue of theſe Armies ſo near one another, time will diſcover; but the Troups of Brandenburg left on the borders of Weſtphalia, under the General Spaan and other Commanders, are now grown to a formal Leger, and have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun already to act as Enemies, being fallen into Munſterland, even to Waren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorp hard by Munſter it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Here in our Country all poſſible care is taken to reſiſt the Enemy, and in this moneth of November, upon the adviſe of his Highneſs, a General Amneſtia was proclaimed for all former differences and inſurrections againſt the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, to be wholy forgotten and pardoned, thereby upon pain of death forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to undertake any account in word or deed againſt the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſtabliſhed by his Highneſs, that ſo the Governours being the better ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, they might unanimouſly watch for the well-being of the Commonwealth: as already for the ſtraitning of the enemy, they have cauſed all Proviſions which are in the open Country, where the Enemy might come by, as Hay, Turf, But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Cheeſe, &amp;c. to be brought into Places of ſecurity, and augmented and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed their Poſts, and the better to defend them, five Regiments of Foot which were going with his Highneſs to Maſtricht, were ſent back, and that no fear of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38464:57"/>
danger might be by the froſt to be ſurprized by the enemy, the Cities of Rotter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Gouda, Delft, the Hague, Leyden and Haerlem, are fortifyed. Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam by its Outworks and ſtrength being made formidable, and ſeats for 320. Canons already placed upon the Wall, of which many are already mounted the moſt being whole, three quarter, and half <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>artowen; the Rivers and Streams with Outlayers filled with Mariners are ſecured, in which poſture we are wayting upon God for his bleſſing on the righteouſneſs of our War.</p>
               <p>This is according to the beſt Demonſtrations and Intelligences, a true Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wonderfull revolutions from the beginning of this unhappy War, unto Decemb. 1672. in this our Land, which not long ſince being at the very top of proſperity and wantonneſs, on a ſudden is caſt down into a poole of all manner of diſtreſſe, in all appearance without any hope of ever riſing again out of the duſt of abaſement, to its former luſtre. What following Ages will give credit to the Hiſtories of this time? What Nations will be able to comprehend the poſſibility thereof? We ſee it before our eyes, and are depending betwixt doubt and aſtonishment: and with great reaſons we ſtand amazed over ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den a ruine, and in doubt, as not knowing from whence this fatall ſtroke is come upon us, at which many have gueſſed; but every one judging according as his Phantaſie leads him, as may be perceived by the Pamphlets and Books ſpread abroad of the cauſes of our diſaſters, whereof ſome are without any ground, other are built on a falſe foundation, and the beſt onely upon probalities, and not on evident Demonſtrations: But for my own part, contenting my ſelf with the bare Relation of what hath paſſed, do commit the further conſideration and judgement thereof unto others.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Faithfully Tranſlated out of Dutch into English, according to the Copy Printed at Amſterdam by <hi>Steven Swart,</hi> Bookſeller. <hi>Novemb.</hi> 30, 1672.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38464:58"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38464:58"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
